<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The treasure of the soule Wherin we are taught how in dying to sin, we may attayne to the perfect loue of God, &amp; our neighbour, and consequently vnto true blessednes and saluation. Many yeares since written in the Spanish tonge, &amp; and [sic] now newly translated into English: by A.P.</title>
            <title>Spill de la vida religiosa. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 202 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 157 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13907</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24208</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121766</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856932</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856932</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22575</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13907)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22575)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 361:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The treasure of the soule Wherin we are taught how in dying to sin, we may attayne to the perfect loue of God, &amp; our neighbour, and consequently vnto true blessednes and saluation. Many yeares since written in the Spanish tonge, &amp; and [sic] now newly translated into English: by A.P.</title>
                  <title>Spill de la vida religiosa. English.</title>
                  <author>Poyntz, Adrian.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 302, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by [John Windet for] Iohn Wolfe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1596.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of "Spill de la vida religiosa", which is erroneously attributed to Miguel de Comalada.</note>
                  <note>Translator's dedication signed: Adrian Pointz.</note>
                  <note>Actual printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank except for woodcut borders.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Spiritual life --  Catholic Church --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:22575:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22575:1"/>
            <p>THE TREASVRE OF <hi>the Soule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherin we are taught how in dying to Sin, we may attayne to the perfect loue of God, &amp; our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto true bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſednes and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
            <p>Many yeares ſince writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Spaniſh tonge, &amp; <hi>and now newly tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into Engliſh: By</hi> A. P.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1. Tim 1.</bibl>
               <p>The end of the commandementes is loue: ſpringing from a clean hart, a good conſcience, &amp; an vnfained faith.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Gal. 5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Thoſe that appertaine to Christ, haue crucified their fleſh, with all the euill deſires &amp; concupiſcences thereof.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON <hi>Printed by Iohn Wolfe.</hi> 1596.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:22575:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22575:2"/>
            <head>To the worſhipfull his good Vncle, Maiſter <hi>Richard Saltonſtall,</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman of the Citty of London, and his wife Miſtres <hi>Suſan Salton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtall,</hi> his louing Aunt.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Adrian Poyntz</hi> wiſheth health &amp; proſperity in the Lord.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I had fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the tran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſlation of this Booke (louing Vncle &amp; Aunt) I remembred the common order &amp; cuſtome euer vſed, in ſo much that few commit their labours to the view of the world, vnleſſe they firſt procure ſome Patrone for their defence. I therefore, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing
<pb facs="tcp:22575:3"/>to ſend my tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the preſſe, before I had committed it to the patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of ſome And ſtanding in doubt to whome I might offer my labour in this kind, truſting vpon your curteſies, did embolden my ſelfe to commende this Treatiſe to your protections. The booke was written aboue an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth and threeſcore yeares ſince in the Spaniſh tongue, the Authour thereof being vnknowne. As for his ſtile and methode of writing I meane not to commend it, leauing the iudgment there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to thoſe, vnto whom ſuch cenſures are belonging. I for my parte as I haue faithfully engliſhed his words, &amp; deliue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red his meaning in ſuch ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that Engliſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may both
<pb facs="tcp:22575:3"/>read his treatiſe and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it, ſo I doo not doubt, but that it wilbe as profitable vnto them that reade it, for their inſtruction, as it hath beene to other nations who haue greedily deſired the tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation hereof. And thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching you to take my good will and meaning in good part, I commit you to the tuition of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worſhips to commaunde. <hi>Adrian Pointz.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:22575:4"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE of the Authour to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE more gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces a man hath receyued of God, and the more he is indued with knowledge of vnderſtanding: the greater puniſhment he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth, if therefore he be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefull. And againe, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer acknowledgeth the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites of God, he alſo by all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall reaſon is bound the more to loue him. Nowe all bookes are repleniſhed with knowledge and learning, nowe is the holy Goſpell ſealed and confirmed with the precious bloude of the immaculate Lambe of God, to the end we may haue a greater
<pb facs="tcp:22575:4"/>aſſurance of the vnſpeakeable loue towards vs. All bookes, I ſay, are full, the earth doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounde with Preachers, ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth as Trumpettes the great power and excellency of the Almighty, for to draw &amp; ſtirre vs vp to lande, praiſe &amp; giue thankes to our Creatour, and moſt louing Father. But we are all ſo prone to vnthanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, and ſo ready to forget his benefites, ſo largely beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon mankind, that there is none almoſt to bee found, who vnfaynedly doo ſeeke him? But all runne and flie headlong into darke and obſcure places of ſin and wickedneſſe. Moued there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the premiſes, I haue fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed this booke, to the glory of God, and (as I hope) to the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of the godly. And becauſe that nowe a dayes our
<pb facs="tcp:22575:5"/>ſlothfulneſſe is ſo great, &amp; our deſire and ſtomacke to the glory of God ſo faint, weake and ſlen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der: I haue vſed here in this my booke ſundry ſimilitudes and parables, by theſe meanes to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice the minds of men the more to the deep conſideration of the contentes of this volume.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:22575:5"/>
            <head>THE TREASVRE of the Soule</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N times paſt there dwelte in a huge and great forreſt, a wiſe and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man: dayly watching, faſting, and praying de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutly, ſeruing the Lorde. Who being deſirous to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, aſmuch as lay in man, to the true and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect knowledge of vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and the loue of God, leauing his cottage, determined with himſelfe to trauaile through all the world, for to ſee if he could find any that wold vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to teach him the ſame. And after greate and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:22575:6"/>weariſome iournyes, met in the ende with a ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, feeding his flocke in a green paſture. He being very glad of this, hauing as yet in none of all his iourneyes found or ſcene any man: came to him &amp; ſaid: Brother I thanke God that I doe ſee thee, wherevpon the ſhepheard bidding him welcome, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked him what hee lookt for in this deſart. I looke, ſaide he, for a knight, who but nowe is gone by this way.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:22575:6"/>
               <head>The ſeconde Chapter doth inſtruct the Paſtors and Teachers of the people.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eſire,</hi> for it was that holy mans name, meruaylinge greatly at the prouiſion, diligence and care which the ſhephearde tooke in his trade: for that he had a crook in his hand, a bagge hanging at his right ſide, woodeen cloge at his feet, and a long coat vpon his backe: beſides at his lefte ſide two hornes hanging at his girdle, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> one ſomwhat bigger th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the other, and two great dogges lying before at his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:22575:7"/>feet, and not farre from thence his cottage enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roned with a hedge of thornes rounde about it. The ſhepherd perceuing <hi>Deſire</hi> to beholde and to view him ſo diligent and narrowly, asked him the cauſe of his wondering, &amp; that if neuer before he had ſeen any ſhepheard. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vppon <hi>Deſire</hi> aunſwered him, how he had ſeene di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of them, but none ſo well prouided and furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed of all neceſſaries as he was, deſyring him moſt frendly, that it woulde pleaſe him to ſhewe and declare vnto him thoſe thinges which hee ſhould in curteſie demand &amp; aske him. The ſhephearde ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing graunted to ſatisfy
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:22575:7"/>him in all his queſtions, ſo farre as he was able or his knowledge ſhoulde reach vnto. <hi>Deſire</hi> began and ſaide, tell mee I pray thee, wherefore carryeſt thou this crooke? Why demandeſt thou mee this queſtion (quoth the ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearde) and thou a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey ſwaine, and a heard-man, and doeſt thou not know this? I do carry it ſaid he, that I might leane vpon it, and keep me from falling when I leade my ſheep about the paſtures. To rule likewiſe my ſheep with it, &amp; to driue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right way, &amp; to keep the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> together that they runne not aſtray, and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eke ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry wayes according to their owne pleaſure. For
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:22575:8"/>when one runneth before and the other behind, then doe I driue the hindmoſt forwarde. And what haſt thou in this bagge (quoth <hi>Deſire.</hi>) Diuers and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry things aunſwered the ſhephearde: Firſt of all I haue a tinder boxt, for to ſtrike &amp; make fyre in colde weather, and to dreſſe my meat for me and my houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde. Beſides I haue in it, breade, ointmentes, a ſmal bottel with oyle, and ſalt, giuing theſe to my ſheep ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times, but chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſalt. Wherefore doſt thou weare theſe woodde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> clogges demanded <hi>Deſire?</hi> for to keep my feete warm when it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, or the drie in raying weather, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the ſhepheard: for
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:22575:8"/>if I ſhould wear fine and proper ſhoes, they would be quickly worne &amp; ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the wet and ſnowe. What doſt thou with this long coate ſaide <hi>Deſire:</hi> It ſerueth to cloath mee (qd the ſhepheard) for if I did not weare this coate, I ſhould not ſeeme to bee a heardeman. But of what ſtuffe is it made (demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Deſire?</hi>) It is made of ſheep skinnes (anſwered the ſhephearde) for if my frocke were made of Wolf skinnes, or of any other kinde of beaſt, the ſheepe woulde ſmell it quickly, &amp; woulde flie and runne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from mee, but nowe that I am cloathed with their wooll, they loue me, know me, and follow me.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:22575:9"/>Tell mee (quoth <hi>Deſire</hi>) what haſt thou in this ſmall horne hanging at thy girdle. Ointmentes (ſaide the ſhephearde) to ointe my ſheepe withall, when they bee ſcabbed. And what haſt thou in the other horne ſomwhat big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then the firſt (deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Deſire.</hi>) Tincture and collour (anſwered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard) to marke my ſheep withall, for to know them again when they are ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled by chaunce among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtraunge ſheep. What doſt thou with theſe dogs. Theſe dogges barke in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> night, turne and chaſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Wolues, for the better ſafety of my ſheepe, and becauſe I ſhoulde the more quietly take my reſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:22575:9"/>without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eare. Wherefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oeſt thou al things ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſedly (quoth <hi>Deſire?</hi>) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>auſe I haue a good boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Lorde (anſwered the ſhepheard) who hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed mee great recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence for my paines, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hough I rather doe this more through the loue which I beare him then for the recompence I doe looke to receiue at his handes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:22575:10"/>
               <head>The third Chapter intreateth yet of the ſame matter.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eſire</hi> did mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nayle greatly at all theſe things, being wonderfully well pleaſed, that hee did all this through meere loue. And tolde him, bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeeing thou ſpendeſt the moſt part of the day in the fieldes, I praye thee canſt thou not ſhewe mee which waye a certaine knight is gone, trauay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vp and downe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out companie, becauſe they haue thruſt him out of his houſe, and his own ſubiectes will not knowe nor receiue him, therefore
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:22575:10"/>doth he ſeek on with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he might dwell &amp; remaine for euer. What is this man quoth the ſhepheard? He is called the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> anſwered <hi>Deſire,</hi> I know where he commonly kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth, ſaid the ſhephearde, and if I had one to looke to my ſheepe, then would I bring thee my ſelf wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her dwelleth, to eaſe thee ſomewhat of thy iourney, for thou muſt know, that he loues ſhepheards, and is glad of their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and although he bee a knight, is notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a ſhepheards ſonne. But becauſe I haue no body to keepe my ſheepe, I will ſhew thee the way as neere as I can. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore brother go through
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:22575:11"/>this deſart and great for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, at the ende whereof thou ſhalt finde a coſtly Pallace, where none but women muſt dwell, who will ſhewe thee where thou mayeſt finde thie knight. For hee is of ſuch frendly and vertuous na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and conuerſation, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hee deſpiſeth no mans co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie nor fellowſhippe. Theſe wordes did very much pleaſe and reioyce <hi>Deſire,</hi> and chiefely becauſe they put him in hope that hee ſhoulde finde out the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> ſaying bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I pray thee ſhew me the direct way, that I may not miſſe my way: I may not leaue my ſheepe alone, quoth the ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearde, but yet I will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:22575:11"/>and get thee good company, that will leade thee God willing in the readieſt &amp; beſt way: take therefore this Dogge for this purpoſe. But what is his name quoth <hi>Deſire:</hi> He is called <hi>Good-wil,</hi> ſaid the ſhephearde. I thanke thee quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> &amp; God haue thee in his keeping. The Lord bee with thee &amp; thy guide, aunſwered the Shephearde, and had him farewell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Of the Pallace of Humility.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen <hi>Deſire</hi> was parted from the ſhepheard, who had committed him to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> way
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:22575:12"/>with his new companio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, being a great comfort vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him in his iourney, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter many nightes &amp; daies trauelling, came at the end vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a Sunday, in a green and large field, very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſante, the grounde neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe being nothing but grauel &amp; very drie: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at <hi>DESIRE</hi> maruelling greatly, how it ſhould be poſſible, that ſo faire and flouriſhing hearbes could growe in ſo rocky a place, ſit rather for thornes and thiſtles, then for any thing els. Eſpied in the midſt of the fielde, a ſumptuous &amp; coſtly Pallace, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he reioyced: and in all paſte going to the howſe, ounde the gates thereof ſhutte, and a fayre Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zell
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:22575:12"/>ſtanding without, by her fauour and outwarde apparell, ſeeming very honeſt &amp; vertuous. Who ſeeing his dogge was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraide of him, and began to ſhake. But <hi>Deſire</hi> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led her not to feare him, becauſe he was not wont to doe harme to any man. <hi>Deſire</hi> maruelling at this Damzell, watching at the gates of the pallace, ſayd: Tel me I pray thee ſiſter, what lookeſt thou here for alone: I tarry aunſwered ſhe, til they open the gates that I might enter in: how art thou called then quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> my name is ſayde ſhe, <hi>Vaine-Glory. Deſire</hi> hauing taried long at the gates, and ſeeing that hee thus watched in vain, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:22575:13"/>to knocke (for at the doore did hange an won hammer called <hi>Patience</hi>) to ſee if any man woul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e come to open the gates. And preſently there came an aunciente and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rende father, being Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and keeper of all the houſe, to open the doores, and his name was the <hi>Feare of God. Deſire</hi> ſeeing this olde and worſhipfull father, after due reuerence done vnto him, ſaide: I am come hither ſir, to look for a certain knight called the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> haue tolde mee howe he ſhoulde bee paſt through thie forreſt, and come into this houſe, therefore full <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am would I know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be here or not The
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:22575:13"/>Porter was glad of theſe wordes, for hee loued in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his brother, and ſaide vnto him. Sonne where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doeſt thou looke for this knight, what buſines haſt thou with him? Moſt reuerend father, anſwered <hi>Deſire,</hi> I doe aſke for him becauſe I doe reioyce in him, and ſtande in great need of him. Howe ſo quoth <hi>The feare of God?</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſaid <hi>Deſire,</hi> I would willingly dwell with him and be his ſeruant, for in all this countrie there is none who liketh mee bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, although I might haue had many others that moſt gladly woulde haue entertayned me. But I haue beene certified of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:22575:14"/>him by others, how he is a noble, courteous, and bountifull Lorde to his ſeruantes. It is moſt true anſwered the Porter, that thou ſayeſt, and not long agone hee came by this way, with ſmal company, yet notwithſtanding, at this preſent hee is not within, but tarry here a while, till I go call a Damoſell, who wil ſhew thee directly, where thou maieſt find him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:22575:14"/>
               <head>The ſeuenth Chapter howe Vaine-Glorie keepeth the watch at the gates of the Pallace of Humilitie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eſire</hi> tarried merily til y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Damoſell ſhold come w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and not long after, there came foorth a very humble and vertuous Ladie greeting him very frendly, and hee likewiſe her, ſaying, I pray thee Ladie tell mee thy name is ſaid wee: <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme me nothing,</hi> &amp; how is this houſe called, quoth hee. The <hi>Pallace of Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie</hi> anſwered ſhe, becauſe there are many Ladies
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:22575:15"/>dwelling in it vnder one ſoueraigne called <hi>Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> And what gentle wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is ſhe, ſaid hee, that watched without at the gates? She is called <hi>Vain-Glorie</hi> anſwered ſhe, wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching continually at the gates till they are opened: and whenſoeuer the Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter looketh not narrowly to her, or taketh ſmal heed to his charge, then ſhee preſumeth oftentimes to come in. Wherefore wilt thou not ſuffer her to come in ſaid <hi>Deſire,</hi> ſeeing her wordes, her apparell and fauour ſeemeth to bee honeſt and vertuous. Ah brother aunſwered ſhee, thou doeſt not yet knowe her, for ſhe is a moſt peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and wicked creature,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:22575:15"/>and although ſhe ſeemeth honeſt by her outwarde behauiour, ſhe is therefore not any thing the better, but rather the worſe. what iniury doth ſhe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto thee ſaid <hi>Deſire?</hi> As much as ſhe is able to do, anſwered the Ladie, for ſhe is daughter to a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked father called <hi>Self-loue,</hi> and to a worſer mother, called <hi>Selfe-Conceit.</hi> Theſe three being our greateſt foes in the worlde, are yet greater enemies to the Lorde, and chiefe of the houſe, called <hi>The loue of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wilt thou know what iniury ſhee doth vnto vs, whenſoeuer ſhee entreth by one way or another in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the houſe, ſhee is very
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:22575:16"/>greedy and hungry, and runneth preſently to a garden, and eateth all the fruites of the beſt tree which wee haue, by the which we do liue onely &amp; are all maintayned: and haue but one of theſe trees, which is not yet ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie fruitful, when ſhe hath thereof ſtolen the fruites away, wee remaine very poore and are ſcarce able to liue. Beſides, which is farre worſe, ſhee is a great flatterer, and hath ſo ſmooth a tong, that when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhe is come within, there is none that is able to thruſt her out againe, but onely our ſoueraigne <hi>Humilitie,</hi> whom when ſhe ſeeth, preſently ſheweth her heeles, and runneth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:22575:16"/>as faſt as ſhee can. Therefore it is beſt not to let her come in: &amp; to this intent haue we made this olde man our Porter, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is ſomething hard and frowarde, and ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly clappeth the doore to her face, and taketh great heed that ſhe enter not by ſtealth, or on a ſodaine. Moreouer wee haue deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him, that hee ſhoulde looke wel to his charge, in opening and ſhutting the gates. <hi>Deſire</hi> wondering at this Ladies wordes, ſaide: thou haſt reaſon not to ſuffer her to come in, ſeeing what great harme ye all receiue by her.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:22575:17"/>
               <head>The ſixt Chapter concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the way to Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ell mee ſaide <hi>Deſire,</hi> who brought thee in this faire &amp; coſtly Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, two Ladies anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſhee, the one called <hi>Contempt of the world,</hi> and the other, <hi>Contempt of her ſelfe:</hi> whereof the laſt is more holie then the firſt. Theſe two Damſelles did guide and conduct me hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and deſired our ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, that it wold pleaſe her to entertaine mee, but ſhee woulde neuer haue done it, vnleſſe it had been for a certaine Knightes
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:22575:17"/>ſake who met vs in the way and brought vs hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and for the loue of him gaue me this garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and receiued mee into her ſeruice. But if God had not granted vs this grace, that wee had founde this Knight in our way, wee ſhould haue taken all this paines in vaine, for ſhee woulde neuer haue enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned me. How doe they cal this knight, quoth <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire:</hi> The <hi>Loue of God</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered ſhee, all which did make <hi>Deſire</hi> glad, and did increaſe his deſire more to ſerue him, becauſe he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Loue of God</hi> was ſo much eſteemed of in this place. Siſter, ſaid <hi>Deſire</hi> of what kindred were theſe two Ladies
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:22575:18"/>who brought thee hither. For it profiteth greatly to vertuouſnes, to be the childe of honeſt and godly parentes, becauſe for the moſt part, the tree taketh her force from the roote. I know their kindred very well anſwered the Ladie, for they bee of a greate ſtocke, and their father is (for they are ſiſters) one of the chiefeſt in the Kinges Court, &amp; is called <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</hi> Beſides I do know their Grandfather, called <hi>Obſeruing:</hi> a very wiſe and ſenſible man, doinge all his things w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> counſel &amp; aduice, who tooke a wife called <hi>Wiſedome.</hi> Then ſayde <hi>Deſire,</hi> The knight who met thee vppon the way, was hee alone, no
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:22575:18"/>quoth ſhee, for hee had a page with him, whom he loued ſincerely, and was called <hi>Neighbourly Loue.</hi> Canſt thou not ſhew mee ſaide <hi>Deſire,</hi> whether this knight is gone? I ſaid ſhe but firſt wee wil go with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and I will bring thee by ſome that will giue thee better direction. But good Lorde, quoth ſhee, what doeſt thou with this great Maſtine: He is giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me ſayd hee, for at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt I had but a ſmal one, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was brought vp in my cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, til I met a ſhepheard who hath beſtowed this Dog vppon mee to bring me in ſafetie through this great Forreſt: How doeſt thou cal him ſaid ſhe, <hi>Good-will</hi> ſaide hee, it is a very good
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:22575:19"/>Dog quoth ſhe, &amp; if thou canſt keepe him wel, thou ſhalt be ſure, as long as he ſhall remaine with thee, that he will not ſuffer any harme to fall vppon thee and thou needeſt not to feare that thou ſhalt go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right way: Tell me ſayde <hi>Deſire,</hi> who ſhal ſhew me this knight? Brother aunſwered ſhee, hee dwelleth far from this place, and thou muſt goe ſeuen daies iourney at the leaſt through this deſarte, before thou canſt come to him where hee dwelleth: There be ſeuen houſes in this deſart, and there is no other hie way but one. But for the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> I will ſhew thee a ſhort foot path, which will ſhorten
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:22575:19"/>thy way, that thou maieſt come the ſooner to thy iourneyes ende: but thou muſt follow my counſell. <hi>Deſire</hi> was glad to heare theſe wordes, and chiefly becauſe ſhe did it onely for loue, and ſaid, whatſoeuer thou commaundeſt mee to doo, that will I doe moſt willingly, for hereby to finde out the <hi>Loue of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this deſart ſaide ſhe ſtand eight houſes or pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces, the firſt is, the Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of <hi>Humility:</hi> the ſecond of <hi>Iuſtice:</hi> the third of <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome:</hi> the fourth of <hi>Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude:</hi> the fift of <hi>Tempera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce:</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſixt of <hi>Faith:</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeuenth of <hi>Hope:</hi> the eight of <hi>Charity:</hi> and in the laſt of all dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> and is ſoueraigne of the houſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:22575:20"/>&amp; all this way muſt thou goe, ſo thou wilt not goe out of thy way. But as I haue tolde thee before, ſo according to my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe will I ſhewe thee a foote path to ſhorten thy way. But firſt of all muſt thou dwell for a time here in this houſe, for to learne marke and remember all our manners, and become acquainted with our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne &amp; her watching maides, and neuer to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get their names nor their countenances. And when thou ſhalt haue had a trial of all belonging to this houſe, and ſhalt bring cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine tokens from vs to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Loue of God,</hi> then ſoon wil he entertaine thee, for the great affection he beareth
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:22575:20"/>to our houſe aboue any of the reſt, and chiefly when hee ſhall ſee a letter from our Soueraigne. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (demaunded <hi>Deſire</hi>) doth this knight loue this houſe more then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? for in my iudgement it is the pooreſt, and bareſt of them all. Thou muſt knowe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this houſe was the firſt builded in this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarte, and all the reſt are ſubiect vnder it. And our commaunder and chiefe gouenour the firſt foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of it, did dwell here, and although hee went in progreſſe oftentimes for to ſee the other his friends and ſubiectes ſo to keepe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in good order, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtanding all this, would not be cald but a ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:22575:21"/>houſe. <hi>Deſire</hi> hauing gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen a diligent eare to her wordes found his hart to bee more inflaimed with Loue, for he did conceiue her meaning very well, &amp; ſaid: that hee would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly remaine there for a time, till her had learned all their cuſtomes. Let vs go within then, ſaid ſhee, and took him by the hand and went to ſhowe him all the houſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:22575:21"/>
               <head>The ſeuenth Chapter concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the talke which Humility had with Deſire.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die had ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him all the houſe, he gret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly maruelled at the fairenes and beauty thereof, and the more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſeemed outwarde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly but verye ſimple and homely and of no great ſhoe, but was within ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry profitable and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, the foundation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was not ſet vpon gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell or ſand, but vppon a fayre and precious ſtone. And after he had ſaide his prayers in the Chappell
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:22575:22"/>ſtanding in the houſe, the Ladie did leade him into the chamber of her Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, who receiued him moſt courteouſly, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe found him ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed and circumſpect in al his words, bad him to ſit down next to her ſide and ſaid: My ſon, wherefore art thou come to vs, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that we are ſo ſimple, poore and deſpiſed? Ah moſt reuerent Ladie, aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered <hi>Deſire,</hi> I ſeeke for a Knight calles the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> and I am told that I ſhall not finde him, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe I remaine for a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine time with your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhippe, and if it woulde pleaſe you, I would moſt gladly tarry here at your obedience and commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:22575:22"/>Thy good will, ſaide the Lady, pleaſeth me well, but firſt of all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thy ſelf, and haue care what thou haſt to do, for not to repent hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. God graunt me grace quoth he, to remaine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in all vertues, &amp; ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt in all godlines. <hi>Amen</hi> ſaid the Ladie. And that it may pleaſe him who hath begun in thee a good worke to bring it to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, for it is neceſſarie that thou ſhouldſt putthy helping hande to it, as much as lyeth in thee, and that God doe accompliſh it. What muſt I do then, ſaid he: I wil tell thee, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the Ladie, if thou art minded to remain here with vs, then thou muſt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:22575:23"/>ſeeke to keepe my daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters fauour, who brought thee in, &amp; take her as thy gouernes, for ſhe is called <hi>Eſteeme nothing.</hi> And wee haue put her in this office to entertaine ſtraungers. becauſe ſhe ſholde inſtruct them, and thoſe that will not be vnder her comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, can neuer remain conſtant or ſtedfaſt. I am ready, quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> to take her for my gouernes and guider in all my actions. But may it pleaſe your Ladiſhip to let me know your name, your kindred, your eſtate, and by what meanes you are become a Soueraigne to all theſe damſels and Ladies, for I was told before I came in, that it was neceſſary
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:22575:23"/>for me to know all this, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by theſe meanes I might loue your Ladiſhip, and all your houſhold the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and likewiſe when I ſhould goe from hence, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I might giue thoſe that ſhould aske mee good di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectious and certayne to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of my former aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding here.</p>
               <p>My name, ſaide ſhe, is <hi>Humilitie,</hi> my father was called <hi>Contempt of himſelfe,</hi> and my grandfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Knowledge of himſelfe,</hi> and my grandmother <hi>Knowledge of God,</hi> and my grandfather was borne in a Citty called <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what thou art, what thou haſt beene, and what thou ſhalt be.</hi> And my grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother was borne in a
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:22575:24"/>Cittie called <hi>Remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the loue God.</hi> And to come to the Cittie where they were borne, there are but two waies and two gates to come in. The one is <hi>himſelfe,</hi> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Creatures.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides they ſay, that none can come into the foreſaid gates but flying, And howe the Lorde himſelfe hath builded the Cittie w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his owne hands, for there is no man able to build ſo great, fayre and ſtrong a Cittie, then he only. How ſaid <hi>Deſire,</hi> the Lord who is ſo excellent, will be bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie himſelfe to make ſuch walles of earth, I, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſhe, for he is a cunning Maſon and delighteth greatly to make walles,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:22575:24"/>and monuments of earth. Wherefore doth hee this, ſeeing hee needeth nor wanteth nothing, quoth <hi>Deſire.</hi> Therefore anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſhee, becauſe hee is ſo bountifull that he will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer bee idle in doing good to others. And of all that he doth, ſeeketh but euery mans health, reſt and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, although the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour hereof apertaine to him onely. And therefore he maketh his workes of ſuch ſlight and vile ſtuffe, as earth, to bee the more prayſed of all. I meruaile ſaide <hi>Deſire,</hi> that ſuch a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and high Lorde wil be praiſed, and feareth not to fall into vaine glory. Not ſo, ſaid <hi>Humilitie,</hi> for he is ſo perfect in all goodneſſe,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:22575:25"/>that no imperfection can any way touch him. And the glorie which wee doe giue him is not vaine, but is his due as belonging vnto him. And although wee ſhoulde giue him as much honor as euer wee could, yet in no wiſe ſhold wee pay that which wee do owe, and much leſſe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to that hee is worthy of. And therefore he will be praiſed and honoured, not becauſe hee is ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but becauſe he is the moſt perfect in all iuſtice &amp; perfection, and will that euery one ſhoulde receiue that which is their owne, and due vnto them: and becauſe wee do owe vnto him which is good alone, al h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>or, praiſe &amp; thanks
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:22575:25"/>he will therefore in iuſtice, that wee doe giue it vnto him. And whenſoeuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other doth deſire or looke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or it, as if it were h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s owne: then may hee well be called vaine-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, ſtealing it from him to whome it onely belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, and is worthy of no better title then of a thiefe, that will ſeeme to vſurpe Gods right, which is due onely vnto his diuine Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:22575:26"/>
               <head>The eight Chapter, wherin Humilitie proceedeth in her words.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eſire ſaid, I praye your Ladiſhippe (ſeeing you haue ſatiſfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me in the reſt) to tell me by what meanes you are become a Soueraign to this houſe, for in my iudgement, it is a great honour &amp; credite. And perchaunce it might be my lucke to bee once a commander of ſuch a like place, for there is great difference to commaund, and to bee commaunded. The Ladie <hi>Humilitie,</hi> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring theſe words began to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:22575:26"/>bitterly. Wherefore <hi>Deſire</hi> demaunded her the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of her ſorrowe &amp; wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping. Then anſwered ſhe, I weep becauſe I ſee thee outwardly &amp; not inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly clad with <hi>Humilitie,</hi> and carrieſt onely the bare name of an aduiſed man, thy heart and mind being notwithſtanding far from it. In vaine haſt thou ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken yet to me, and til now haſt thou diſſembled with vs all, becauſe ſuch thoughtes and deſires do vtterly diſpleaſe my God and Father, who being man in this worlde, and hauing taken vppon him our ſhape and nature, ſought not with words or deedes to commande, but rather to be commaunded
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:22575:27"/>of the ſimpleſt. And who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer keepeth not this way, taketh the high way to condemnation, miſſing the right path leading to eternal life. Ah poore and miſerable wretches that ſeeke to command and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect others, hauing more then inough to command and gouerne themſelues. whoſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uer hunteth after this honour, ſeeketh care, griefe, trauaile, paine, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe and danger. O hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie burthen that bringeth to a man but paine and griefe, &amp; the il will, gaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay, and murmuring of thoſe that were bounde in duety to recompence labor with thankes and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe: which tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhalt finde to bee moſt true
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:22575:27"/>if thou remayneſt but a while with vs. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſhoulde ſatiſfie thee vpon thy demande, I will not hide fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee this ſecrete, but for the <hi>loue of God</hi> open and diſcloſe to thee my hearte. When I came firſt to this houſe I humbled my ſelf as a ſlaue and ſeruant to all the reſt of the damſels, which lowlines I haue continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſo loued, and embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, that the mercy of God did marrye mee to this minde as to a huſband, by whoſe means I haue got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten this office, although I did vtterlie deteſt it and refuſe it. When <hi>Deſire</hi> did hear this, be honoied this Ladie greatly in his hart, &amp; eſteemed her to bee very
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:22575:28"/>vetuous y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wold for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Loue of God</hi> becom ſo humble &amp; lowlie: and ſaid, nowe doe I ſee whoſoeuer will become a gouernour and commander of others, muſt firſt of all followe your Ladiſhips ſteppes, and learne to be humble &amp; cammanded. It is ſo my ſonne anſwered ſhee, and if thou didſt vnderſtande <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne right, then thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt perceiue that they are not my wordes but the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting truthes. How ſhoulde I vnderſtand the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quoth <hi>Deſire?</hi> Thou muſt knowe ſaid ſhee, that hee who humbleth himſelfe, ſhalbe exalted, although he doth not humble him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to that intent to bee exalted, for by theſe means
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:22575:28"/>he ſhoulde fall into pride, and humilitie and pride are contraries one to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: For if one hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth himſelf in any work which he taketh in hand, in on wiſe may he become proude of it, although in his worke conſiſteth hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, yet in himſelfe (humbling himſelfe to ſuch an ende as I haue ſpoken of) ſhoulde conſiſt pride and ambition. And becauſe the worke taketh his name and title from the intent of a mans minde: it happeneth that ſuch humilitie is properly termed with the name of pride and arrogancy. And to ſpeake more plainly of this, humility is not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether contrary to pride,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:22575:29"/>ſeeing they do remaine at one time in one body to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether (which is contrary to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nature of contraries) but the ſpirite of the one is quite repugnant to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo that they can not abide one anothers ſight, for humilitie is onely the worke, but the ſpirite of humilitie maketh a happy end of the ſame, together with the good intent for to humble himſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:22575:29"/>
               <head>The ninth chapter doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the former words, &amp; of the battaile between the fleſh and the ſpirit.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His my lowe minde ſayde <hi>Humilitie,</hi> is my faithfull helper, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender, in a battaile which I dayly ſuſtaine againſt a mighty Princeſſe of an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pallace, who hath a great ſorte of Ladies vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her iuriſdiction: and her court is called, <hi>the Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of Pride,</hi> and the ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne thereof, <hi>the Pride of life.</hi> Euery day ſhee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth or to contende and quarrel with me couering onely to ſearch out mine
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:22575:30"/>eyes. And bringeth with her the lifetenaunce of her houſe, commonly called <hi>the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cupiſcence of the fleſh,</hi> with her ſteward, <hi>the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence of the eyes,</hi> theſe three are accompanyed with an other wicked woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their mother, who hath nouriſhed them all, called <hi>Obliuion.</hi> But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe is oftentimes of no force, and very weake, therefore ſhee bringeth w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> her a fooliſh idiot, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brideled watching maide called <hi>Maliciouſnes,</hi> beſides <hi>3.</hi> other more, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Wrath,</hi> the other <hi>Sloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes,</hi> and the third <hi>Enuy.</hi> And with theſe two laſt, there comes two other named <hi>il Suſpition,</hi> &amp; <hi>falſe Iudgement,</hi> theſe are alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:22575:30"/>my mortall ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, againſt who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I am forced to ſight &amp; to ſtriue: &amp; whenſoeuer they haue made an entrance here in our houſe, then by the lowneſſe of my minde I driue them out again, and doe giue them the foyle. But when I &amp; my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany haue done this, then muſt we be carefull onely but for one thing, which is diligently to looke that this damſell called <hi>Vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory</hi> (continually keeping ſentinell at our doore) doe not enter, for when ſoeuer ſhe cometh within, then ſhe doth robbe vs of al the profite, delight and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, which we take in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer comming in others, ſo that we can no wiſe enioy
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:22575:31"/>the fruits of our pain and trauaile: and when theſe other Ladies, ſayd <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire,</hi> make an entraunce here within, for to enda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage you, wherefore doth not ſhee that ſtandeth without at the gates come in w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them. Becauſe aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered <hi>Humilitie,</hi> that the other Ladies haue wings and neuer enter through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doore, but flie alwaies o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the wals of the houſe, and oftentimes doe hyde themſelues in ſome corner of the houſe, &amp; lie in am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſh, for to aſſault vs whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we think leaſt vpon them. Therefore it is moſt nece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſary that wee ſhoulde watch and warde conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually, that we be not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted being altogether
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:22575:31"/>vnprouided for to fight. Let vs ſpeake ſome thing more plainer of this point quoth <hi>Deſire.</hi> Wherefore doe you contende &amp; ſtriue with them, ſeeing it is not well done to giue an euill example to others, which happeneth, when men ſee ſuch iars, ſtrifes and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, betweene wiſe and godly people, who ſhould be merciful, meeke and bountiful for the <hi>Loue of God</hi> towards euery bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. We battell and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with them, ſaide <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie,</hi> and ſeeke to driue them out of our houſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are mortal ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> who is our onely Lande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorde, &amp; in matters which are contrary vnto him, we
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:22575:32"/>ſhoulde nor will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, or enter in league w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any body.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>The tenth Chapter doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat of the concupiſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the fleſh and how to ouercome it.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He good will &amp; loyalty which Lady <hi>Humilitie</hi> did bear to the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> did wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully delight <hi>Deſire,</hi> and ſaide, Madame I woulde be glad that it woulde pleaſe your Ladiſhippe, to ſhow and teach mee the meanes whereby, you doe vſe to ouercome theſe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Ladies, your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:22575:32"/>and driue them out of your houſe. I wold to God, aunſwered ſhee, that thou wert herein ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfied, but becauſe I doe not yet know thy nature, will, and mind, but onely by certain external ſignes, whereby one may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued, it cauſeth me ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to doubt of your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty: for honny is not ſweet to euery body: for the diuerſity of ſundry na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and complexions: My Soueraigne, quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> euen as I am here, and as your Ladiſhippe doth ſee me, ſo I yeeld my ſelfe into your power, my reaſon and will wholly ſubmitting to yours, that I might receiue inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by theſe meanes for
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:22575:33"/>to find out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Loue of God.</hi> Moſt willingly wil I the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſatiſfie thy minde aunſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Humilitie,</hi> and diſcloſe all my ſecrets, &amp; commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate vnto there my day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie exerciſes.</p>
               <p>Firſt, my godly pretence and purpoſe beinge my huſband (whereof I haue ſpoken vnto thee before) made mee by the meanes of Contempt, to ouercom the worlde, and by chaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and faſting to rule my one fleſh, and to vanquiſh Sathan by humilitie, and make mee Soueraigne of this houſe, but chiefly of my ſelfe, which is the moſt of all. For when my fleſh feeleth that I trauell and endeuour to pleaſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Loue of God,</hi> then it doth reſiſt
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:22575:33"/>me with all his crue, &amp; is continually diſquieted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my doings, but neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe my ſoule doth then remaine in peace, content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and quietneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deſire</hi> did meruaile greatly at the wordes of Lady <hi>Humilitie,</hi> and ſayd, I pray your Ladiſhippe, that it may pleaſe you to inſtruct me by ſome ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in theſe things, for I am ſomewhat dull of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, ſo that I ſhal better conceiue your mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by an example or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon. This motion did greatly pleaſe <hi>Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> and chiefly, becauſe ſhe ſaw how he did begin to waxe humble, in confeſſing the dulneſſe and groſſenes of his wit and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:22575:34"/>and ſaid: My childe, whenſoeuer any of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaide women doe enter in, then I behaue my ſelfe in this ſort, as for example: when <hi>Concupiſcence of the fleſh</hi> beginneth to ſiruit with me, before ſhe is able to come to mee, I knowe her, and her conditions very well, for ſhee is verie gluttenous, and gathereth forces by eating and drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, therefore I with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe from her all dainty kindes of meate, and wil not giue her ſo much of ordinarie diet as ſhe doth deſire to haue. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe my forces are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to withſtand or to va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh her, (for mine owne houſhold commeth to aide and to aſſiſt her) I craue
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:22575:34"/>and call for helpe at the hands of God, who ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth alwaies at my ſide, to ſtrengthen mee againſt theſe wicked women. Moreouer, I doe eſteeme my ſelfe to bee as a beaſt who doeth eate no more then his maiſter doth giue and allow him. But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his maiſter ſeeth that he is greedie at his meate, hee doth reſtrayne his mouth with a mufle, becauſe hee ſhould not eate but at ſuch times, and ſuch as it doth pleaſe him to giue vnto him. Wherefore the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> my onely maiſter hath put about my mouth a muſſell called <hi>Sobrietie,</hi> that I ſhould eat no more then will ſuffice nature, &amp; hath tolde me that I ſhold
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:22575:35"/>of that, yet ſomething w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe, if I woulde pleaſe hun. In this forte is this wicked Ladie vanquiſhed and ouercome, as much as it doth concerne my owne ſelfe, But becauſe ſhe doth not onely aſſault me with mine owne fleſh, but by others, doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke and draw me to ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualitie and vncleanneſſe: therefore I auoide her as much as I am able, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewing all things wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſhe ſeeketh to intice me to her loue and liking, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeming this to be the beſt and only cemedy to eſcape her ſnares and deceytes. Furthermore. ſhee aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> onely my body, but alſo my mind with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and ſtraunge imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:22575:35"/>and thoughtes: for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which to auoid like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, I iudge it the beſt remedie, to caſt my mind vpon my Sauiour Chriſt, and continually to behold his death, paſſion &amp; mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome, as alſo to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pames of hell, the ſtraitnes of the laſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and my ſmall en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, and that I muſt appeare before the tribunall ſeat of God, to giue an account of al my words, thoughts and deedes: And by theſe means is ouercome, van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed and quite ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne this wicked wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, being Lieuetenant to the <hi>Pallace of Pride.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:22575:36"/>
               <head>The xi. Chapter, Ladie Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie ſpeaketh againſt the Concupiſcence of the eyes, and the pride of life.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T auailed not to haue ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one vnles I ſhold endeuour my ſelfe alſo to vanquiſh the other her fellow and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, who is Steward of this vngodly Pallace, &amp; is called <hi>Concupiſcence of the eyes.</hi> And oftentimes ſhee offered firſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, but I ouercome her by my godly intente and purpoſe, ſaying: whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer that ſhee is ready to come. In vaine doeſt thou ſeeke to aſſault me, for I
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:22575:36"/>am not unlike to a beaſt, that doth care for no thing but what is before him, &amp; eſteemed of no other ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluitie, but what hee needeth, and therewithall is contented, being no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing curious in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which he lacketh, nor carefull whether the Saddle and the Trappi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs are cleane, neat or old, or whether the ſtable or maunger be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether fit for him or not, but is ſufficiently ſatiſfied when he may ſtand or lie, for to take his naturall reſt. And becauſe I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme my ſelfe to bee ſuch an other, for the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> I will vſe my body according as they are v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: for when the maiſter doth mark that they waxe
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:22575:37"/>wilde and ſtubborne, hee putteth a bit and bridle in their mouth to rule them after his owne will. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe bath the <hi>Loue of God</hi> brideled mee with a bitte called <hi>Sham<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtnes,</hi> that I ſhoulde not curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly beholde and loue vanitie, for it is daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to beholde that which is forbidden to bee deſired or coueted. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Loue of God</hi> hath giuen me warning, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>euer I ſhoulde come to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>euer I ſhoulde come to ſee a thing which is beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull, comely and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to the eyes, that I ſhoulde not ſet my minde oppon it, but ſhoulde di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine it as a trifle of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and ſhoulde conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually loue and behold y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:22575:37"/>cheefeſt felicitie, being a a treaſure not ſubiect to mutability, or vnconſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie which is my only Sauior Jeſus Chriſt, who doth ſeeke and demaunde my heart and loue, and will moſt bountifully reward me for the ſame. And by theſe contemplations I ouercome the other Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſell. Now when theſe two are driue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away, there reſteth yet the laſt, who is there Soueraigne to bee vanquiſhed, who hath more deceite and ſubtiltie then all the reſt, &amp; watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth continually ouer the good workes of a man, and is called the <hi>Pide of life.</hi> And whenſoeuer the commeth, ſhe is alwayes accompanyed with one
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:22575:38"/>page or an other, the one called good, and the other <hi>euill intent.</hi> But ſo ſoone as I doe ſpie her, then I vſe her in this ſort: &amp; tell her, Auoid thou wicked &amp; deceitfull Syren, for if I ſholdgiue eare to thy ſweet poiſoned words, I ſhould draw vpon me a ſea of ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities &amp; miſeries. And although thou clounſelleſt me that I ſhould grudge at the chaſtenings &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of others, yet I will not hearken to thy wordes, for I tell thee plaine, I thinke that hee loueth me, who doth cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten and rebuke me, for not to come to ſhame, and vtterly to bee caſt away. Sometimes ſhe doth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent her ſelfe vnder the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:22575:38"/>of Enuy and tels me. This bodie is in ſuch au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and this hath ſuch a commandemente, but no bodie eſteemeth of thee. The one is Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, the other Lieuete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, the other Steward, &amp; ouerſeer the other: but thou art accounted but as a kitchin drudge, being notwithſtanding vs old &amp; as good as any of them al. Thou art without office or commaundement, and eſteemed amongeſt them as a ſlaue of all ſlaues, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they neuer commit any charge to thy handes, therefore thou mayeſt wel ſee, that he who doth moſt is leaſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered of, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after then vſe thy ſelfe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, for whoſoeuer
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:22575:39"/>maketh of himſelf a ſheep, the woolfe wil quickly eat and deuoure him. Theſe and ſuch like things doth ſhe caſt before me, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth diſſembling wiſe to me, although I knew her not, nor could perceiue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence theſe lamentable words did ſpring &amp; grow. Whereupon I aunſwere her in this ſort. Content thou thy ſelfe, I haue not forſaken the worlde, and mine owne ſelfe, to rule &amp; command others, but to be gouerned &amp; commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded my ſelfe: Long agone haue I purpoſed to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient, and therefore I will doe that whereunto I am called. For God wil neuer aſke an account of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> commandement which I
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:22575:39"/>had here in this world, &amp; how highly I haue beene aduaunced in Office and authoritie, but howe I haue behaued my ſelfe in mine eſtate, howe I haue executed thoſe thinges which were commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded mee: how I haue humbled my hearte to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes him. Therefore I will diligently execute the vocation whereunto God hath called mee, and meddle not with other mens offices and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. For I am aſſured of one thing, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is a ſtep &amp; degree to ſaluation, to bee obedient, dutifull &amp; hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, from which no man can fall but by an aſpiring minde. And therefore I haue no occaſion to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:22575:40"/>for this my baſenes ſake, but rather the more to thanke and praiſe the Lorde, and greatly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, that hee hath taken away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me all occaſions of feare and perill, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto honour and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie doo oftentimes leade &amp; bring a man. And herein let Saynt Auguſtine ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfie thee, who ſaith: In nothing haue I felt more Gods wrath, then when he appointed me to rule &amp; gouern others. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my ſonne maruaile not of this, for euen as this wicked Damſel, who is Soueraigne of the pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of <hi>Pride,</hi> is more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted and giuen to all manner of iniquitie and wickedneſſe, ſo we of our
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:22575:40"/>ſide do need to be the more circumſpect, ſtrong &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent for to auoide her ſnares and ſubtilties. And to bee ſhort, I will ſhewe thee here a thing of no ſmall importance, being a remedie whereby thou mayeſt vanquiſh, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome all theſe wicked crue together at once, or els euerie one apart. For when one of them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, whoſoeuer ſhe be in complayning wiſe, do the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as I doo: Namely, when the <hi>Concupiſcence of the fleſh</hi> commeth, complay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that they giue her too little &amp; too cold cheer, or that her drinke is too ſmal or too ſowre: then I anſwere her: It is moſt certaine that he who hath
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:22575:41"/>more then hee deſerueth, hath no reaſon or occaſion to complaine: &amp; thou doeſt not deſerue a cruſt of breade, nor a cup of colde water, as the beſt Saints haue confeſſed in truth of themſelues, and therefore thou doeſt deſerue a great deale leſſe, who art not to bee compared vnto them in holines of life, being ſo vnſtedfaſt in Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and ſo vnthankfull for his benefites. What occaſion haſt thou then to complaine, ſeeing thou haſt more then thou art worthy of. And the ſame I tell her likewiſe, when ſhe miſliketh her apparel. The like anſwere I giue vnto the other, called, <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence of the eyes,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:22575:41"/>ſhe ſtirres and prouokes me with the deſire of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueting this or that: ſaying to my ſelfe: O thou vile &amp; poore wretch, that which thou deſireſt vnder the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of neede, is ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y and contrary to the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie of the ſpirite. And although ſhee is not by this altogether ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding it doth diminiſh at the leaſt our ſelf-loue &amp; pride in our vertues. And we Chriſtians (who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the name of Chriſt) ſhould bee aſhamed to bee endued with leſſe vertues, then the Heathens and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters were, amongeſt whome Seneca was the onely mirrour and pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of vertuous pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:22575:42"/>as it is yet manifeſtly to be ſeene in his workes and writinges. The like aunſwere I make to the thirde Damſell being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Pride of life,</hi> when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhee goeth about to tickle me with a deſire to be honoured, eſteemed of, exalted, and to command, thinking within my ſelfe: O thou miſerable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, thou doſt inioy more honor then thou art wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of, if thou couldeſt onely conceiue it. For haſt thou not deſerued to burn in hell fire with the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſoules? And beholde what honour the Lorde doeth ſhewe thee, to ſuffer thee to dwell in peace and quietneſſe amongſt his creatures, I and which is
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:22575:42"/>more, hath receiued thee in to his ſeruice, &amp; hath made thee one of his domeſticals &amp; houſhold. And although y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art altogether vnworthy to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt of his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, yet hath he choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee to be one of his minions, &amp; wil not let thee part from him night nor day, but requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that thou ſhouldeſt ſpeake with him continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and praiſe and thank him for his goodneſſe. Moreouer hee dooth feede thee in this tranſitorie and mortall life, euen with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread of Angels, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thee at his own table for to banquet with him. Thou proud wretch what canſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u craue more<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> where wouldeſt thou clime? wouldeſt thou fall
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:22575:43"/>downe again from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce thou art come, for to lie as deep in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bottomles pit of hell, as thy father Lucifer doth? what wouldeſt thou haue more? doeſt thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to bee God himſelfe. Thou lackeſt nor needeſt nothing, O vnhappy creature as thou art, open but only thy blinded eies, and confeſſe that thou haſt more then thou deſerueſt, or art worthy of. Be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> that, that God ſendeth thee, and with thine own eſtate, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade thy ſelfe that all things which do happen, do come to paſſe by Gods ordinaunce and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:22575:43"/>
               <head>The twelfth Chapter doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat of the waies and means to vanquiſh the other wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen theſe three are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eaſily mayeſt thou ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe her, who is their nurſe and mother, called <hi>Obliuion,</hi> who comes cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping into the houſe through a thouſand holes, ſometimes ſhe findes her ſelfe in the morninge, ſometimes in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueninge Prayers, and ſometimes at our worke
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:22575:44"/>and labour. And alwaies I rebuke her in this ſort: I tell thee woman, there is no man that keepeth a beaſt in his ſtable to bee i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle alwaies, and to take his pleaſure onely in ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, drinking, &amp; ſleeping, but that hee might worke dayly with ſome courage. For whenſoeuer a beaſt is not tamed with working, faſting and watching, hee groweth quickly ſtubborn and ſtiffe necked agaynſt his maiſter. But when the mayſter ſeeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is ſlow and nothing quicke, then he vſeth a goade or ſpurre to driue and prick him for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde: euen ſo hath the <hi>Loue of God</hi> procured for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e a rodbe called <hi>Feare,</hi> whereby he driues mee
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:22575:44"/>forwarde. And I that am ſeruant &amp; the pooreſt of all the houſe, know ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie well that a ſlaue is not kept but for to worke and trauaile, &amp; no bodie ſhould make great accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of him or eaſe his taſke or feede him daintily, becauſe hee ſhould not waxe too bold or too ſtubborne: for there is no worſe man then a wicked priſoner. Further I aſke her, whether the kingdome of heauen is to be gotten w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eating, drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſleeping, and ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of life? Not ſo truely, for our ſauiour Chriſt did not enter into it in this ſort: &amp; ſeeing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he who is our onely guide, did not take this waye to come thether, but by paines and
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:22575:45"/>ſufferings entered into e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting bleſſednes: ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore if we wil obtaine the ſame ioy, then are we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to walke in the way of ſufferinges and pouertie, for when the head will go this way and the feet ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the bodie ſhall neuer be ioyned and come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And if we do not keep the high way of ſuffering, trauaile, paine, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, then wee can in no wiſe be incorporated, but ſhall bee cut off as vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable members and bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and be caſt into Hell fire. And if we refuſe to be partakers of his croſſe &amp; paſſion, then we ſhall not participate of his ioyes and reſurrection. And if wee doe not finde Chriſt,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:22575:45"/>in puniſhing our fleſh, as he was whipped, ſpitted at, deſpiſed, wearied, poor, hungry, thirſtie, and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring death betweene two theeus as an il doer, being neuertheles bout ſtaine or ſpot, and altogether in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, then wee are ſure neuer to taſt of his ioyes, and inioy his louely and ſweet countenance, being nowe made kinge of all kinges, &amp; Lord of Lords: ſometimes this wicked woman comes to aſſault mee, when I am in my chamber at my prayers, although ſhe were weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and troubled with too much heate or froſt. Then I tell her, woman a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout damſell feeleth no te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſnes of a good thing.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:22575:46"/>Beſides, what ſhal I pay to the Lord againe, for all that hee hath giuen mee? What can I ſuffer to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite my deere and welbe-loued Sauiour Chriſt? Who through meere loue, hath loſt his life vpon the croſſe, not lying there at his owne pleaſure, as I do heere, but was throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en moſt cruelly vpon it, &amp; there ſtretcht out as with a racke, not cloathed, but naked, not vnder a couer, but vnder the bare ſkie: not with warme ſhooes at his feete, but pearced w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great and cold iron nails, and all this for my ſake. Wherefore then ſhould I grudge to ſuffer a thing of nothing for the loue of him? All which is yet ſmal
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:22575:46"/>in compariſon of the reſt, for he hath not onely, moſt gladly and willingly, for my ſake ſuffered the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and calamities of this life, not for an houre, a day, or a moneth, but for three and thirtie years to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and beſides remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned three hours aliue vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the croſſe, in ſuch pain, grie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, and martirdome, that no tongue is able to ſpeake it, or any vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it to conceiue or comprehende it, all which ſeemed little vnto him for the great loue and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he bore to all mankind, and particularly to euery one of vs, &amp; would haue ſuffered much more if it had beene needful: he not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding being a king,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:22575:47"/>and I worſe then a ſlaue, he God, and I more vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then the earth, duſt, or aſhes: he moſt holy and innocent, and I a great and grieuous ſinner, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of ſeuere puniſhment. And ſeeing hee hath done all this for my ſake, ſhold I think it too much to do any thing for the loue of him? And is the ſeruaunt better then the maiſter? Therefore <hi>Obliuio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> auoid, for it is no paine for me to be here, ſeeing I doe not ſuffer any griefe or aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie: and vnleſſe I ſhould do this with a good will or ſpiritual pleaſure, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hande of God might fall vpon me: for it is written, Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is hee who doeth the worke of the Lorde neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligenly
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:22575:47"/>and careleſly. For hee cannot abide that one ſhoulde ſerue or offer the ſacrifice of prayſe and prayers vnwillingly, but is pleaſed whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſpring and come out of a ioyful &amp; vnfayned minde. When now this olde and accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed wretch is ouercome, then muſt wee endeuour ourſelues to vanquiſh the other fooliſhe watching maides, whome the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer they are, of the greater and of more force are their temptations, &amp; aſſailings: and the leſſe they are mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, the vncaſier are they to bee rebuked and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen. Now when the firſt whereof I haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken called <hi>Maliciouſnes,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> her daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:22575:48"/>
                  <hi>Wrath,</hi> do both aſſaile me, then I giue them this anſwere. Charitie is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull &amp; patient, and thus with my good intent and meaning my huſband, I quite ouerthrowe them. Further, I tell them, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mine acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, who profeſſe great loue and frendſhippe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes me, doe offer mee ſome ſecret wrong and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury, ſeeing that I deſerue and am worthy of more, I am willing to beare it pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Loue of God,</hi> &amp; perſwade my ſelfe that they greatly fauour mee, that they offer mee not ſo much as I, (if all thinges were rightly conſidered off) haue deſerued. And this the Lord ſuffereth for
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:22575:48"/>my ſins ſake, for to make me readie in this worlde, that I might learn to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſome thing in the mean ſeaſon for his cauſe. Thoſe whome thou ſayeſt that wiſh me ill, and do ſpeake ill behind my backe, and cannot abide my ſight, they hate not my ſoule, but my ſinnes onely, my faultes and wickedneſſe, therefore I am bounde to loue them, for their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and intent is good &amp; goodly. And if I am Gods ſeruant, I ſhall ſoone ſpy &amp; hate mine owne faults. Wherefore then ſhould I curſe or wiſh any harm to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who do that which I would endeuour to do my ſelfe? I will therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, &amp; therewithall driue
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:22575:49"/>thee away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me. Thoſe that do report ill of me, &amp; ſeeke to hinder mee, are they not my brothers and ſiſters, and ſeeing that they be ſuch, am I not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to loue, and in no wiſe to hate them, by force and vertue of the comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, <hi>Loue thy neighbor as thy ſelfe?</hi> And whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhee doth aſſault mee with another of her ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes called <hi>Enuie,</hi> who bringeth with her a two edged ſworde, commonly termed, <hi>Spight at another mans corporall and ſpiritual vertues.</hi> Then I anſwere her as followeth. But firſt of all you muſt know that ſhee is a venemous and ſpightful Damſell, for ſhe withereth, conſumeth, &amp;
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:22575:49"/>killeth her ſelfe at the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie and good ſucceſſe of her neighbour, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiueth againe, and reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth at their miſerie and aduerſitie. But nowe to my anſwere. Thou ſayeſt that others are endued with greater wealth, beauty, and better giftes of nature them I, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I doe reioyce and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count me the happier, for in this and in the life to come, I deſire nor wiſhe for nothing but for Ieſus Chriſt, who is the Angels and my onely treaſure, mine and all creatures beauty, my gaine, and the fountaine of al goodneſſe. Therefore let thoſe loue the other things that wil, as for mee I doe thirſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:22575:50"/>nothing but after Chriſt and his loue. Fe, there is no exception of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rich or poore, of the foule and faire with him, but hee regardeth onely the humblenes and lowlines of the ſpirite. And thou ſayeſt that others do poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe ſuch and ſuch wealth, and that they receiue great giftes, and I none at all: and I doe ſay, although they inioy all this, that I poſſeſſe, yet much more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they, for I beare ſo greate and noble a minde, that I eſteeme it a great baſenes to ſettle my heart vppon ſuch meane, vile, &amp; tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitory things, as all earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things are. But now I wil ouerthrow thee w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, whereof I beare the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:22575:50"/>name and tel thee that the children of God do freely poſſeſſe all theſe gifts, and many more, &amp; not I that am but a ſlaue, and not worthy of the leaſt of theſe thinges. Then ſhe turneth her backe quickly, and preſently aſſaulteth me w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ſpirituall enuie of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans goodnes and holines of life, ſaying, this man is more aduiſed, more ſeruent in prayers, quieter, more mortified &amp; ſoberer then thou art? Whereupon I do anſwer her &amp; I ſay: Let vs nowe ſpeak with reaſon. Where<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ſhold I ſpight at this, ſeeing they pricke me for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde to godlineſſe, and giue me an occaſion to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce; when I ſee that my
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:22575:51"/>good Lorde and mayſter hath ſuch ſeruantes, who are lo feruent and holy, &amp; do loue him ſo much with out diſſimulation. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the more I am bound to pray, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it would pleaſe his diuine maieſtic to beſtowe more giftes and graces upon them, to the end he might be prayſed &amp; honoured the more by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For if one did loue his mayſter, would he not be glad that he were know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, loued and honoured of all the world, and that he likewiſe ſhoulde inrich them with a temporal and ſpirituall riches and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſednes. Auoide therefore thou aceurſed and wicked creature, for thou knoweſt not what charity meanes,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:22575:51"/>ſeeing thou art the brood of ſo wicked a damme. Therefore I tell thee far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I would be glad (ſo that it might bee without the damage of my ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) that my Lorde and God ſhoulde depriue mee of all theſe bodily and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall gifts, wherewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all I am endued, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow them vppon others, who ſhould uſe them bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to his glorie then I who am vnworthy of the ground whereon I tread, and moſt vnthankefully haue entertayned his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces &amp; fauours ſo aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly beſtowed vppon me. For I deſire nothing elſe then the glorie and praiſe of my Lord &amp; may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, &amp; if it were poſſible,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:22575:52"/>upon mine own charges, although my ſelfe ſhoulde receyue no benefit by it at all. Doeſt thou not know that our Gob doeth all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hings in great wiſedom? hee knoweth the veſſelles before, whereinto he pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his graces, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee knew me to bee vnfit for ſuch fauours, for my vncleannes &amp; prides ſake, that woulde bee puft vp with a vain preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my ſelfe, mine own workes &amp; vertues, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath his wiſedom not beautified me with them, and yet I am wel conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and will deſire no more then I am able to vſe, both to his glorie and mine owne ſaluation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:22575:52"/>
               <head>The thirteenth Chapter ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth moſt manifeſtly the waies and meanes to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome all manner of wickedneſſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Aliciouſnes</hi> third daugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, is <hi>Sloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes,</hi> who is of a wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked nature, becauſe ſhe is in all ſpirituall actions which concerne Gob, in whome conſiſteth all our ſaluation, very cold, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent and ſlothful. And when ſhe beginneth to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault me, then I do with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande her with theſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours: In dayrie doeſt thou ſeeke thou accurſed
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:22575:53"/>wretch, to draw me from my prayers and ſpirituall exerciſes, and therefore to ouercome thee I will bee more diligente, &amp; zealous in praying, watching &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, to paſſe my time in godly conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plations: And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe ſeeth that I thus prepare my ſelfe to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, ſhee taketh another courſe with me and ſaith: Doeſt thou not ſee &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that thou art altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without feruency, &amp; that thou ſhalt praye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aginſt thy ſtomack, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Gob is rather prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked unto anger, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by pleaſed, and rather tempted, then honoured, who both deſire to be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with a burning zeale and ioyful minde, and not
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:22575:53"/>with an vnwilling and browſie heart. Wherevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I do aunſwere as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, auoid hence thou brood of Sathan, too wel do I vnderſtand thy mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: for thou muſt know that at ſuch times I doe pleaſe God much more, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſerue him at mine owne charges, then when hee beſtoweth a great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance of grace vpon me, for it is an eaſie thing for him to ſwimme that is holden vp by the chinne. Doſt thou not know that hee withdraweth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times his graces fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs: for to trie what we will or are able to doe our ſelues. And when hee ſeeth that we doe offer and preſent vnto him all our abilitie,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:22575:54"/>and do al that lyeth in vs, hee doth then at conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent time through his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie increaſe our comfort a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: and although we bee depriued of that zeale which wee ſhoulde haue, yet notwithſtanding wee feele alwaies in vs a good will &amp; deſire to performe it, and a miſliking of that which wee dot: and doeſt thou aſke then, wherefore I doe embolden my ſelfe to pray, being altogether faint, ſlow and of no zeale, and moreouer art not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to ſay: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo doing is to tempt God: I tell thee, if I had yet leſſe fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uencie then I haue: yet I would not be afraid to do this, and woulde preſent my ſelfe before my Lorde
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:22575:54"/>&amp; ſay nothing vnto him, nor craue any thing at his hand, but onely ſtande be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him. ſhewing him honour and reuerence, hoping that he is preſent, and doth vouchſate to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold &amp; regard me, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hee which is the fire of loue, will kindle my hart whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it ſhall pleaſe him. For I will yeelde my ſelfe altogether into his hands and ſubmitte my will and my ſelf wholly vnto him: and further knowe, the colder and famier I am, the more neede I haue to approche neere to the fire. For if I ſhoulde go away from it, I ſhould be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer and waxe colder. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoid thou hence therefore for I do not ſet my ſelfe to
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:22575:55"/>pray, or to ſpirituall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templations, and other godly exerciſes, for to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue thereby comfort on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or becauſe I finde in it a ſweet and pleaſant taſt, but to ſerue my Lord and God, &amp; beſides I know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his wil for to do it, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing my ſelf to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of his name in all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and holines. Nowe when this wicked Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell doth perceyue that ſhe is not able to drawe mee from the loue of my God by theſe meanes, ſhe tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth her aſide, and ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours to allienate mee from y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> loue of my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, by the helpe of theſe two other foreſaide dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, called <hi>Ill Suſpition,</hi> &amp; <hi>falſe or light Iudgement,</hi> for
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:22575:55"/>to diſpiſe them in my hart and iudge them to be wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and malicious, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before my eyes all that which might breede in me ſome ill ſuſpition of them, for by theſe meanes to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice me to giue a falſe and raſhe iudgement of their doings. And to bring their purpoſe to better effect, they come accompanied w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Murmuring, Deſpiſing,</hi> and <hi>Backebiting.</hi> But preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I aunſwere th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n as it followeth: it doeth not become a ſlaue ſuſpect ill of his betters, ſinners ſhould not touch ſacred things, I muſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme euery bodie to bee good and holy, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count my ſelf to be wicked and a ſinner, not knowing
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:22575:56"/>what euery man may bee in the ſight of God, or els what his latter ende will be. But as concerning my ſelfe, I know whom and what I am, and to what end the feelt of my deſires <hi>Wickedneſſe</hi> and <hi>Vngodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> woulde bring &amp; carrie mee, namely into hell, it y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mercy of God came not to aide or aſſiſt me. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I haue inough to doo with my ſelfe, and to ſee whether my thoughtes, doodes, and conſcience bee good, for I know my ſelfe and not other men. As concerning others, I wil take and chuſe the ſureſt, which is to thinke well of them all, wherewith I ſhall looſe nothing, but may profite and aduance
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:22575:56"/>much. For it is daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to refuſe the certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for the vncertainty: and charity thinketh no harm. Moreouer, who hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned mee a Iudge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God &amp; my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour? betweene him and his conſcience? truely no body. Therefore auoide, the iudgement hereof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to God onely, for it is hee that ſeeth the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward? thoughts, and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth euery mans reynes &amp; ſecrets. Moreouer <hi>Ill Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition,</hi> proceedeth from y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Diuell, and is quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to brotherly vnitie, and cauſeth great ſtrife a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt friendes, which a man may finde to bee true by daylie experience: for if a huſband taketh an euill
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:22575:57"/>ſuſpition againſt his wife, and ſhe doeth perceiue it, although ſhe had been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the honeſteſt of all her goodly neighbours, ſhee wil quickly turne her cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie into all manner of wickednes and diſloyalty. For it is moſt true that <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca</hi> ſaith: <hi>Ill ſuſpition hath cauſed many men to ſinne.</hi> What although they haue erred, perhaps they are fallen through weaknes, or els through great temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, but notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all this, I ſhoulde not therefore hate them, or els giue a light iudgment of their doings, but for the <hi>Loue of God</hi> ſhoulde turn all things to the beſt, ſhould ſuffer, pittie, and haue compaſſion on them.
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:22575:57"/>And if thou wilt not yet graunt mee this, then I tell thee that it is Gods iuſtice and iudgement, whoſe prouidence doth bring all thinges to paſſe, which in no wiſe wee are able to comprehende: and in ſuch ſort, that eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as he neuer ceaſeth to doe good vnto vs, ſo he permitteth theſe faultes, and turneth them (although they are euill) to the aduantage &amp; profite of thoſe that are fallen, or els of theirs that do behold them. Therfore trouble mee no more, for he that taketh vppon him to iudge other men, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumeth vppon the title of God, and remember what happened to thy father, when he would haue been
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:22575:58"/>like vnto God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I haue reaſon to take warning by his &amp; others miſhap, and miſfortune, &amp; to haue a ſpeciall eye to mine owne actions and doings.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>the xiiij. Chapter endeth the exerciſes of Ladie Humilitie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eſire</hi> being ſtroken in a maze at Lady <hi>Humi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lities</hi> words ſaid: Now firſt I do vnderſtand that, which long agone I haue heard my aunceſtors tell, but yet neuer had any tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of it, namely that <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie</hi>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:22575:58"/>conteyneth and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth all manner of vertues, Iuſtice Peace, Ioy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſpirituall and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall comfort. Therfore I pray your Ladiſhip to reſolue mee of one doubt which troubleth me not a little, as touching this matter. Whether you doo know alwayes theſe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Damſels, when they come in diſguiſed apparel or vnder the colour of godlines, for we do reade, that they are able to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form themſelues into An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of light, whereby ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily they may deceiue the ſimple, and ſuch idiots as I am. Ah my welbelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſonne, quoth <hi>Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> this is a great point. Therefore to reſolue thee
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:22575:59"/>herein, thou muſt knowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God hath put a Lampe in the midſt of our Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, called <hi>Good conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,</hi> which burneth day and night with the oyle of his mercy: and is kindled with a wike of the holie Scriptures, &amp; hangeth to it a ſtring called <hi>Care of the mind,</hi> being faſtned at a naile called <hi>Care of inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> And as long as this Lampe doth burne and is kindled, then wee neede not to feare them, for wee can ſpie them quickly. And although they come as diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed as they may, yet we know them by their going, for they are crooked miſhapen, and are lame, and do halt, ſo that they cannot for their liues go
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:22575:59"/>ſtraight and vpright. But my ſon, when this Lamp is put our, by our owne negligence: or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the nayle falleth out by our idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, or els that the ſtring breaketh, or that God w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draweth his Oyle (which he neuer doth before wee doo firſt ſpill it willingly) then we remaine in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and nothing doth proſper with vs. And therefore we pray to God alwaies, that it woulde pleaſe hun to lighten our Lampe, and doe ſay with the Prophete Dauid, O Lorde thou art my guide, lighten mee therefore in darkeneſſe. The Lorde graunt you his grace and mercy, quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> for you haue comforted my
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:22575:60"/>troubled mind. Take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaid <hi>Humility,</hi> theſe Ladies whom I ſhall aopoint, in thy companie, vntill thou be ſufficiently armed with a <hi>True feare,</hi> for the foreſaid wicked Damſels will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour themſelues to draw thee perforce againe out of our handes, Here is <hi>Fortitude,</hi> againſt the firſt called <hi>Concupiſcence of the fleſh. Earneſtneſſe</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Concupiſcéce of the eyes.</hi> The ſecond, <hi>Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie,</hi> againſt <hi>Price of life.</hi> The third, <hi>Watchfulnes,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, <hi>Slothfulnes.</hi> The fourth <hi>Bountifulneſſe,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Maliciouſnes.</hi> And ſo the Lord haue thee in his keeping.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:22575:60"/>
               <head>The fifteenth Chapter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treateth of the Ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ues of Lady Humilities d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ughters.</head>
               <p>By theſe means ſaid <hi>Humilitie,</hi> with the helpe and grace of God, &amp; mine owne endenour, I van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh and ouerthrowe all my enemies. <hi>Deſire</hi> did receyue a great comforte by his ſoueraigns words, and ſaid, I pray your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhippe giue me leaue to go viſite theſe Damſelles, for to come acquainted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them. Go in the name of God aunſwered ſhee this leaue I giue thee moſt willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:22575:61"/>And thou my Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, go thou with him, &amp; bring him acquainted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all the houſholde. And herewithall <hi>Deſire</hi> depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted moſt ioyfully out of his Soueraignes cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, accompanied with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foreſaide Lady, who was Steward of the houſe, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Eſteeme nothing.</hi> Who brought him preſently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chamber of <hi>Humilities</hi> eldeſt daughter, called <hi>Confeſsion of ſins,</hi> who did entertain him moſt frend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and being bidden to ſit by her, began to ſpeake. I pray you Lady y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it may pleaſe you to tell me your eſtate, conditions, and manners. I aunſwered ſhe, am <hi>Humilities</hi> eldeſt daughter, and a ſcholler to
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:22575:61"/>this damſel our Steward and do greatly delight in her company, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging and confeſſinge alwayes whome I am, &amp; ſuch as I eſteeme my ſelfe to be. <hi>Deſire</hi> preſently did marke, that this Lady was of a great contenance and very bountiful, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe ſhewed her ſelfe to be an enemie to all vain glory, and idlenes, and herewithall, did take his leaue of her. And being departed from thence, his guide brought him to the Chamber of Lady <hi>Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities</hi> ſecond daughter, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Deſire to bee diſpiſed,</hi> who did receiue him like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe moſt cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>teouſly, and ſitting downe by her, ſaid: I pray you Lady to tel me
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:22575:62"/>your name, &amp; condition. I am called, ſaid ſhe, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be deſpiſed, contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and nothing eſteemed of?</hi> This did greatly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maze <hi>Deſire,</hi> hearing that ſhe was ſo deſirous to be diſpiſed and contemned, ſeeing that it was quite contrary to euery mans nature and condition: yet notwithſtanding, did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count and eſteeme her a very vertuous and godly Damſell, becauſe ſhee did it for the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> And herewithall did take his leaue of her alſo, and went with the Stewarde his guide to <hi>Humilities</hi> thirde daughters Chamber, who was called <hi>Glad to be deſpiſed,</hi> who entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him likewiſe with a
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:22575:62"/>cheerefull countenance, &amp; as he ſat downe, ſayd vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her. I pray you Ladie to tell me your name and conditions: I aunſwered ſhe, do reioyce to be diſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, contemned, iniured, &amp; mocked at, and this for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Loue of God. Deſire</hi> did maruaile at her vertuous diſpoſition, and ſaide: I pray you to teach mee the means whereby I might attaine to your vertues, for I find this, which you haue to bee quite repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt to mine owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: for when I am iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, contemned, diſhono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and nothing eſteemed of, then I grudge and waxe angrie at it. This doth happen ſaid ſhe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou haſt notyet em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:22575:63"/>
                  <hi>Humilitie,</hi> who doeth comprehende to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme nothing of her ſelf, and for the <hi>Loue of God</hi> to deſpiſe her ſelfe: but it is a ſure and certaine token that thou art full of <hi>Selfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loue, Pride,</hi> and <hi>Ambition.</hi> Yet becauſe God hath brought thee here in the houſe, we will teach and inſtruct thee in all kind of vertues, and pull from thee this thicke and filthie ſkin, and tranſforme thee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto a new ſhape, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare thee, that thou maiſt come to the ſpeech of the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> Therefore if thou wilt attaine to my vertues, firſt of all thou muſt imbrace my ſeconde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſter, called <hi>Deſire to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſed,</hi> oftentimes remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:22575:63"/>and ſpeaking to thy ſelfe. Hereafter I wilbe deſpiſed and contemned, &amp; not grudge, when I am mocked at, iniured &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied. And when thou haſt attayned vnto this, then ſhalt thou be feruent in prayer, and with great la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, not at the firſt, but by little and little obtaine this vertue, whereof I do beare the name. And although this will fall ſomething hard vnto thee at the firſt, becauſe thou ſhalt be forced to ſtriue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thine owne nature, yet ſhalt thou with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie ouercome all diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie, inſomuch that thou ſhalt at the laſt reioyce, when they ſhall eyther in wordes or deedes, offer
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:22575:64"/>thee, any wrong or iniury. Therefore force thy ſelfe to beare patiently all ſhame, contempt &amp; deſpiſing, for thou muſt knowe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> none is iuſt vnles he be hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble, and grudgeth not to bee deſpiſed, iniured, &amp; moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked at. wherevpon <hi>Deſire</hi> did aunſwere, and ſaid, I doo maruell that he ſhold be vniuſt, who doeth miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like and grudgeth at theſe thinges? for there are few to be found y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> then are iuſt, therefore I think y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> you do miſtake your ſelfe in this point. Not ſo ſayd ſhe, and therefore I will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct thee in this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine. Firſt thou canſt not deny, that hee is iuſt, who doth deſire to giue and to receiue of euery man his
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:22575:64"/>right. And thou knoweſt that vnto man appertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth nothing but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and mockery, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee is more vilder then any other creature, for his great and abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſinnes: and therfore I conclude, that hee who grudgeth to receiue his due is vniuſt.</p>
               <p>Furthermore thou canſt not deny, that all good thinges ſhold be beloued, ſought for, and eſteemed of, and ſo much the more, the more that they exceede in goodneſſe. And contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwiſe, that euery euill thing ſhould be hated, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed, &amp; ſuppreſſed. And it is moſt certaine, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man is naught and wicked, becauſe God one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:22575:65"/>is good, and therefore it followeth, that hee with reaſon ſhould be diſpiſed, ſcorned, and hated, becauſe it is his due and right.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>The ſixteenth Chapter ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that all thinges which God hath created are good, and howe this title Good, belongeth onely vnto him.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ehold ſaid <hi>Deſire,</hi> I am not yet ſufficientlie ſatiſfied w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe your argumentes, where with you doe ſeeke to prone, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God onely is good, and all that, that is not God ſhoulde bee naught. For
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:22575:65"/>your concluſions do diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, where ſhee witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, that when God did beholde all that hee had made and created, founde it not onely to bee good, but perfecte and without fault. Further, ſeeing that God is good (being our cheefeſt felicitte, and of all that there was created, the efficient and onely cauſe) conſequently it muſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe, that all which hee hath created ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding good, becauſe the worke ſhoulde be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to the excellency of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> workman, for not to ſtain his ſkil and cunning And ſeeing that man is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt nobleſt &amp; excellenteſt crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of all viſible thinges,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:22575:66"/>therefore hee is not good onely, but exceedeth in goodnes, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, according to your owne argumente, to him belongeth all honor, loue, and obedience. I will not anſwered the damſell, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute with thee any longer, but I will more at large, declare and expound vnto thee theſe thinges, to the end thou maieſt the better vnderſtand them. Thou muſt know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God onely is good, (as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Goſpel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the onely truth doeth witneſſe) which is thus to be vnderſtood. That God in his eſſence and nature is good onely, &amp; that it is proper to him to be good, and al that God hath cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated is good, but by parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:22575:66"/>of his goodneſſe. Therefore when the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth conſider the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable goodneſſe of God, and wayeth his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites and graces, beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vppon her, ſhee will yeeld all honour and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience that is due to his Maieſtie. And this tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to Godwarde, and not the creatures. And in this ſort ought we to loue our ſelues &amp; all creatures, becauſe wee were all good in our firſt creation: and therefore man ſhall not ſeeke to bee honoured and reuerenced for his owne ſake, but for the goodneſſe of God participated vnto him: and becau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e he is the handie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke and crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God, ſhall attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:22575:67"/>onely vnto him all his goodnes, and not to himſelf or to his owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie. For th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re is great difference in that hee hath receiued of God, and in that he hath of his owne: from God hee hath that which is good in nature, but from himſelfe that which is euill: for by him he doeth carry his image and likeneſſe alwayes in him: but by himſelfe, through his wicked and vngodly life, doeth deface it, and becommeth altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnlike him, delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in nothing by nature, but in that which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to God, and his firſt creation. And hereout may we perceiue that we ſhoulde honour and loue
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:22575:67"/>that which man hath in him of God, namely, his good nature, condition, &amp; all kinde of vertue. But ſhoulde hate and deteſt in him all that he hath of his own, namely his wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, filthines and ſinne, in ſuch ſort that wee ſhall in ſundrie meanings, and to ſundrie endes, honour or deſpiſe, loue or hate a man. And how holy or vertuous ſo euer a man is, yet muſt he know and confeſſe that hee hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of himſelfe, but all manner of wickedneſſe, &amp; ſhall therefore deſire, that the honour and praiſe of goodneſſe ſhall onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to God, from who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all goodnes floweth. But as much as concerneth
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:22575:68"/>his wickedneſſe being his owne, ſhall wiſh onely to bee diſpiſed, contemned, diſcredited, and diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for it. And whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he ſhall doe this, then ſhall hee bee iuſt. And if a holie, good, and vertuous man doeth not grudge, &amp; is deſirous to be diſpiſed, why ſhould a ſinner then account it iniuſtice and vndecent to haue ſuch a deſire, but contrariwiſe would bee honoured and eſteemed of although they had deſerued it. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no ſinner ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade himſelfe that hee doth much when hee deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to be thus deſpiſed &amp; diſdained, ſeeing a holy, vertuous, and iuſt man, is bound in duty and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:22575:68"/>to deſire it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>The ſeuenteenth chapter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treateth of the ſame words.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He wordes of the Damoſell did greatlie pleaſe <hi>Deſire</hi> &amp; ſaid, I praye you that it may pleaſe you to tell the means, wherby I might further and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne this holy deſire. Two meanes there are, aunſwered the Ladie, the firſt is the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> the ſecond a <hi>godly minde,</hi> and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſoeuer thou wilt take my counſel it will greatly further thee to the attay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this my vertue. Moſt willingly, anſwered
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:22575:69"/>
                  <hi>Deſire,</hi> I wil take it: make account then, and fully per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wade thy ſelfe ſaid the Damſell, that the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> whom thou deſireſt and loueſt ſo much, hath no greater enemy, nor one who offereth hun more wrong and iniury, &amp; more reſiſteth him then thine owne fleſhe. Therefore take this for an vſe and cuſtome, to ſpeake euery morning to thy ſoule as followeth.</p>
               <p>Let me ſee, O my ſoule, how thou wilt hate this day thy rebellious fleſhe, mortall enemie to thy cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator, Lorde, and louing ſpouſe Ieſus Chriſt, and what meanes thou wilt vſe to deſpiſe and vexe it: And again in the euening
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:22575:69"/>ſhalt thou ſay this vnto her. Let vs examine now my foule, howe thou haſt hated this day thy vile bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die enemie to thy onely Lorde and Sauiour, and haſt ſought by all meanes to diſhonour it, chaſten it, and vexe it, and how dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent thou haſt beene to hinder it of his owne wil, and in all thinges to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute it. And brother, whenſoeuer thou wilt go about to do this, and with a ſtedfaſt deſire to hate thy Lordes and thine owne ſoules enemic, then will this exerciſe bring and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce thee to a high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of humilitie, and by little and little worke in thee a perfection of all vertues: ſo that ſhortlie
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:22575:70"/>after thou ſhalt deteſt thy ſelte, hate &amp; vanquiſh thy owne rebellious will and fleſhe. And whenſoeuer any body doth vſe thee ſo, then take holde of mee, and of my vertues, and herem greatly alſo reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, ſay: Praiſed and bleſſed: bee the Lorde my God, who giues me now meanes to bee reuenged vppon mine enemies. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire</hi> receiued great comfort by this damſels wordes, and with great and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thankes, hauing take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> leaue of her, was brought by his guide into another of Ladie <hi>Humilities</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters chambers, called <hi>Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie</hi> or <hi>Simplicitie,</hi> who likewiſe receiued &amp; enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamed him moſt trendly,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:22575:70"/>and curteouſly placing him, next to her ſide, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſpeake of God, and of heauenly and ſpirituall matters. Wherevpon <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire</hi> did pray the Damſell, that it would pleaſe her to tell him her name. My name is <hi>Simplicity,</hi> anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſhee, and with euery man I deale plainely and without deceite, vſing no diſſimulation in any of my actions or doinges, &amp; all that I heare or ſee, doe alwaies conſter it to the beſt: for I thinke euery man to be as I am: at the leaſt as much as concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his mind, I thinke no harm of any man, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of my ſelfe, for I haue alwates an euill ſuſpition of my ſelfe, hauing an eye
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:22575:71"/>continually vpon all my thoughtes and deſires being very circumſpect &amp; carefull to eſchew y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> traps and ſnares of the wicked, that by theſe meanes I might waxe ſtrong and increaſe in my mother <hi>Humilities</hi> vertues. How, anſwered <hi>Deſire,</hi> can you not bee vertuous vnleſſe you be thus carefull? No ſaid ſhe, for <hi>Simplicitie</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Wiſedome</hi> is worth little or nothing, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth more then it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth: for the <hi>Loue of God</hi> loueth none but thoſe which walke wiſely and circumſpectly in all his waies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:22575:71"/>
               <head>The eight Chapter intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of Sincerities man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> pray you good Lary (quoth <hi>Deſire</hi>) to tell me ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> you deale vpright and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cecely with euery <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. In three things an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered ſhe, in thoughtes, wordes, and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>edes. Firſt of al I will not caſt my thought vppon matters which do paſſe my vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding or capacitie, nor ſeeke to purchaſe honour, dignitie or prouiotions of this world, which are but vaine and tranſitorie, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies thinking my ſelfe
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:22575:72"/>to be the worſt amongſt al reaſonable creatures, and the vnworthieſt of all Gods ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, eſteeming all others to be holy, good, and repleniſhed with hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly graces &amp; vertues. Secondly, I will not vſe any flattering or deceitfull words, to intrappe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with my brother, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I, no, for all things els are wicked, &amp; ſpring out of the roote of vanitie and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlenes. Thirdely, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraine my ſelfe from vain, fleſhly, and worldly acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and endeuour to doe that onely which is ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, plaine and proſiable, thereby to eſchue <hi>Vanitie,</hi> &amp; <hi>Partialitie,</hi> which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight cauſe and worke my cuine and ouerthrowe: for to
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:22575:72"/>go alwaies roundly and plainly to worke, it main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned the mind in humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, whereof the contrary is full of feare and danger. wherefore is the contrary thus perillous? qd <hi>Deſire,</hi> thou muſt know that my mother hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me two iewels or precious ſtones to keepe, which I haue here in my Cloſet, the one called <hi>Chaſtity,</hi> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Innocencie,</hi> which are of ſuch valour, price and eſtimation, that none is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to giue the worth for them. For we doe direct all our actions by theſe two iewelles, euen as the Marriner doth his ſhippe by the compaſſe, endeuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring euery day to get the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; hauing gotten the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſurely
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:22575:73"/>to keepe them. And when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer <hi>Curioſitie, Vanitie,</hi> or <hi>Partialite,</hi> are ſuffered to enter through the doore of our harte, mouth, eyes or eares: they they ſerue by all means to ſteale the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away and depriue vs of theſe iewelles. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whoſoeuer doeth not direct all his thoughtes, wordes, and deeds, to ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and keep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them, deſerueth to be eſteemed worſe then a foole. What will you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſaid <hi>Deſire,</hi> with theſe iewelles, for it is a token of couetouſnes, to poſſeſſe ſuch needleſſe and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous riches, as iewelles and precious ſtones bee, where you ſee ſo many poore almoſt ready to ſtarue for want of foode &amp;
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:22575:73"/>maintaynance. Not ſo quoth ſhe, for thou doeſt miſtake my wordes. And although that in the loue and deſire of poſſeſſing wealth, riches, and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly goodes, after the intent and meaning of the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor or owner thereof, ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conſiſt couetouſnes, fraud and guile: yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding there can bee no deceite or auariſiouſneſſe in poſſeſſinge of theſe iewelles, whereof I haue ſpoken, becauſe wee doe deſire and keepe them to ſerue and pleaſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> and to honour him herewith, when hee vouchſafeth to viſite vs. Other riches eyther periſh by wormes, or conſume with ruſt, or
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:22575:74"/>weare with time, becauſe they are earthly, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to euery man. But thoſe that are hidden in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> harte, no muſtines, ruſt, worme, or tune can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume them, becauſe they are common to none but to ſuch as doe poſſeſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Dow, quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> if hee who doeth poſſeſſe them, did diſcourſe and make a ſhow of them, would they not conſume then, as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther riches doe? No ſaid ſhe, for when he doeth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer them to bee ſeene, then hee doeth not poſſeſſe them any longer, for who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer doeth inioy them, doeth not thinke that hee doeth poſſeſſe them, but doeth alwaies endeuour himſelfe and trauaileth to
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:22575:74"/>get and to attaine vnto them. For our God doeth oftentimes beſtowe theſe iewelles vppon him that doth not know them, and is ignorant of the poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thereof, becauſe that our <hi>Preſumption</hi> and <hi>Selfe loue</hi> which lyeth hidden in our hartes, ſhoulde not ſteale them away. Therefore he that doeth poſſeſſe them, keepes them as ſecret as may the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:22575:75"/>
               <head>The nineteenth Chapter ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, what thinges that mayntaine ſinceritie or Simplicitie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He wordes of this Damſell did pleaſe <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire,</hi> &amp; ſayd, by what meanes might one beſt keepe then theſe iewelles? one thing aunſwered ſhe is moſt requiſite and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to thoſe that are new begin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers, and not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether vnprofitable to the long continuers, which is to flie &amp; to ſhutte doores and windowes, for to haunt and frequen many mens companies, and to heare and ſee much, are
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:22575:75"/>ready waies to loſe and to be depriued of them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our ſoule is as a looking glaſſe, which ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily receuieth all figures and likeneſſes which are brought before it: and is like vnto waxe which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth the print &amp; marke of any thing put vppon it. How is it poſſible, quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> to flie and to ſhutte all the gates and win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes for hun that dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in a congregation or companie of many? for he is conſtrained to go often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times hether and thether for to diſpatch his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, beſides it is both de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and godly to be affa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and curteous to euery man, for not to fall in the vice of <hi>ſelfe-loue</hi> or <hi>Partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie,</hi>
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:22575:76"/>which is to bee ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred and to be deteſted, although it ſeemeth to carrie a faire ſhine or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of vertue and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. It is true anſwered ſhe, but neuertheleſſe the <hi>Loue of God</hi> commandeth vs that we ſhould be cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect in all our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and doe nothing but by neceſſitie according to the greatnes of our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, and to bee carefull alwaies for theſe iewels, which we haue in our cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody, that we do not loſe them. How muſt we then behaue our ſelues, quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> for to doe as much as lieth in vs? It is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full anſwered ſhe, that hee who is not able for his buſines ſake to keepe him
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:22575:76"/>from company, indange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring hereby greatly the looimg of theſe two iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els <hi>Chaſtitie</hi> and <hi>Innocency</hi> ſhould alwaies take me at his ſide, and whenſoeuer he ſhall bee in my compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, then he needeth not to feare, that hee ſhall looſe them, although he ſhould trauel through al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world. I pray you, quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> that it may pleaſe you to inſtruct me by ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon, that I might the better conceiue it, and the ſimple and idiot people y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better vnderſtand it, for to carrie it away in their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories the more eaſier. Knowe then, aunſwered <hi>Sinceritie,</hi> whoſoeuer is deſirous to keep <hi>Chaſtitie</hi> and <hi>Innocencie</hi> (being two
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:22575:77"/>of the beſt meanes to ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> readieſt waies to come to the laſt, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Loue of God,</hi> who comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all perfection of <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie</hi>) muſt flie and ſhutte doores and windowes. And if it be not poſſible for him to doe it, let him vſe me then, in all his actions and put mee in his right eye, that whenſoeuer his left eie of <hi>Concupiſcence,</hi> of <hi>raſh or fooliſh iudgement,</hi> will deſire to ſee or iudge any thing, let him direct her to his right eye of <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie,</hi> conſidering with himſelfe earneſtly, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man or woman are Angelles, and children of the Lorde, who continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally without ceaſing doe laude &amp; praiſe their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:22575:77"/>Likewiſe whatſoeuer he ſhall heare or ſee of his neighbour, his right eye ſhall excuſe it, and amend it. And whenſoeuer his left eye of <hi>Concupiſcence,</hi> ſhall ſeeke to drawe him to the loue and deſire of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Creature, let him pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently beholde his right eye, which will ſend him to the remembring &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the beauty, goodneſſe, and other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of his Creator, which will cauſe him to loue the creature, for no other cauſe but that ſhee doth loue, laud, and praiſe with him her God and Creator. And therefore it were moſt requiſite, that he ſhould vſe me like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in all his words and
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:22575:78"/>communications. When quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> doeth a man all things with <hi>Sinceritie?</hi> when his minde, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſhe, is ſimple, vpright, and ſincere, ſo that his wordes and deedes be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies correſpondent, and all his actions reaſonable and without diſſimulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Hauing alwaies a ſpeciall regard that all his doinges may redound to the glorie &amp; praiſe of God, his ſoules health and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and to the profite of his neighbour: and this doing is in all thinges to walk with <hi>Sinceritie,</hi> and he goeth ſure and without daunger, whoſoeuer ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth her alwayes in his companie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:22575:78"/>
               <head>The twentith Chapter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treateth of Pouertie, one of Ladie Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eſire</hi> hauing receiued great comforte out of <hi>Sincerities</hi> words, tooke his leaue of her, and his guide brought him to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother of Ladie <hi>Humilities</hi> daughters, called <hi>Pouerty.</hi> who bidding him wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, did pray him to ſit downe by her ſide. <hi>Deſire</hi> ſeeing the great courteſie of the Ladie, ſaid, that hee was very glad of her co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, becauſe he did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that ſhee eſteemed
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:22575:79"/>much of the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> and therefore did aſke her name, and prayed her to tell him her manners and conditions. My name, quoth ſhe is <hi>Pouertio.</hi> And for the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> I doe not poſſeſſe nor care for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye worldly thinges. wherein, quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> take you then your ioy and all your comforte? My chiefeſt treaſure, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered ſhe, wealth, and riches, ioy and comforte conſiſteth, to forbeare all things for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Loue of God.</hi> I doe greatly maruaile of this, quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> for I was tolde, that this pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace was builded, by the moſt nobleſt, richeſt, and moſt bountifulleſt knight of the earth, wherefore
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:22575:79"/>doth he ſuffer then ſo poore and needie people to dwel in it? For I cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue what profite or gain hee receiueth by your po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, need, and neceſſitie. I will tell it thee, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſhe. The Landlord &amp; the founder of this houſe, is Lord and King of all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, hauing al her riches and wealth in his hand &amp; power, and yet it is his will and pleaſure, that we ſhould bee poore, becauſe we ſhoulde not ſettle our heart vpon any thing, but vpon him onely, for hee is able inough to giue vs all things aboundantly. But theſe whom he loueth, he doeth giue them none of this earthly felicitie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſhoulde onely
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:22575:80"/>deſire and loue him, and hate this tranſitorie and deceitfull worlde. The greateſt token and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes which we can haue of his loue towardes vs, is when hee doeth not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vs in this wretched worlde, or beſtoweth on vs all, that our fleſh and luſt doth craue and deſire. Moreouer he doeth ſende vs pouertie, becauſe wee ſhould not bee too penſiue and carefull for the goods and riches of this worlde, but that wee ſhould ſerue him with an vnfayned minde and a ioyfull ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, and not lightly for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny worldly thinges, gaine or loſſe, proſperitie or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie, receiue a vaine ioy, or diſcomforte, but
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:22575:80"/>that our hearts ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies in reſt and quiet, without perturbations or diſcorde, bee vnited with God our creator and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour. For the <hi>Loue of God</hi> is of ſuch tender and gentle nature, that he can not dwell but in a quiet, cleaue, &amp; peaceable place. which is your cheefeſt vertue, quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> my cheefeſt vertue is, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Pouertie,</hi> to frame and conforme my ſelfe to the godly and vertuous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation of the children of God, whoſe company I gladly do frequent. And although my deſire is, for to haue nothing yet for to ſhut out a wild bore who doeth deſtroy all our gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, called <hi>Partialitie</hi> or <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:22575:81"/>of perſons,</hi> my mother hath ordained that I ſhould liue as the other of my ſiſters do. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſhold not loſe the rewarde of my vertue, ſhe hath married me to a holy mind, called <hi>to deſire no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing:</hi> this quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> in my iudgement, is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire more then to be good, or more then wee do owe or are bounde vnto, for I do perſwade my ſelfe that your Landlorde doeth counſell you rather to the pouertie of the ſpirite, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to that of the boly, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophet ſaith, if thy goods and wealth doeth increaſe ſet not thy heart vpon it: Therefore I eſteeme that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertue of pouertie doth not conſiſt in poſſeſſing
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:22575:81"/>little or much, but in the hart and mind of the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſor. It is true, quoth ſhe, that the vertue of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie conſiſteth in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, yet for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Loue of God</hi> to forbeare theſe thinges it is a precious vertue, &amp; worthy of great praiſe &amp; commendation. For our loue and deſire is ſo much enclined to the beauty and comelines of theſe earthly thinges, that hardely we can poſſeſſe them, without fixing our whole minde vpon them. And becauſe they ſhould not draw vs away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the loue which wee beare to God, which commonly is very ſmall, it is good and wiſely done to take the flaxe from the fire, and to remoue &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:22575:82"/>all occaſions of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, as much as lyeth in vs. For the loue of God wil haue all the heart and can abide no partner: and take of this an example of our Sauiour himſelfe, who could haue poſſeſſed all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wealth of this world, &amp; that without to ſet his minde vpon it. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I pray thee how poor hee and all his Apoſtles were. What doth this els ſignifie, but that we ſhold abſtain from theſe things which are ſo dangerous &amp; draw many y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> doe poſſeſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into euerlaſting paine and damnation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:22575:82"/>
               <head>The twentie one Chapter intreateth of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eſire</hi> was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe comforted by this Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, and tooke his leaue of her. And his guide brought him to an other of Lady <hi>Humilities</hi> daughters, called <hi>Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> whom he greatly did reuerence, for her counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce and outwarde ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paraunce did ſhowe, that ſhe was of great dignitie and more eſteemed of, by the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> then any of her ſiſters were. And when he did offer to kiſſe her handes, ſhee woulde
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:22575:83"/>not ſuffer it, for ſhee was one of Ladie <hi>Humilityes</hi> daughters, and ſought not after Honour and Promotion. But ſhe bad him to ſit downe by her wherevpon <hi>Deſire</hi> did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire her name and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions. My name, quoth the Lady, is <hi>Obedience,</hi> &amp; I am married to a huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band called <hi>to leaue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing vndone,</hi> who is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry valiant, and renowned Knight, and hee onely is able to ouerthrowe this feareful and terrible beaſt, ranging thus in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world. called <hi>ſelfe-will.</hi> Which beaſt doth deuour all thoſe that follow and loue him, and cauſeth through his ſweet whiſtling, al the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly to follow him, and
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:22575:83"/>fewe doe leaue him before hee hath brought them to eternall deſtruction. But euery body flieth away from mee, although it bee moſt true, that without me, none can get and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> And ſeeing that God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen me ſo good a huſband, therefore I doe nothing but that hee commandeth me: Likewiſe I craue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at his handes but neceſſaries: and I neuer do go about any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone for feare of theefes, for here are many, and hide themſelues, ſo that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee them. Who goeth then with you, quoth <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire,</hi> firſt aunſwered ſhee a truſtie dogge, called <hi>Good wil,</hi> and my ſiſter <hi>Sincerity,</hi>
                  <pb n="158" facs="tcp:22575:84"/>and my daughters, <hi>Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight, Mirth, Diligence,</hi> and <hi>Chaſtity,</hi> and before all things my mother <hi>Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie</hi> will alwaies accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie me: all theſe muſt I needes take with mee for to goe ſure, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out daunger, and for to do thoſe thinges which are commanded me. I praye you quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> to tell me in what ſort your mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Humilitie</hi> is alwaies with you in all thinges which you take in hande: for I cannot well vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande it. Of all thinges which I doe, aunſwered ſhee, although they were the greateſt of the worlde, I thinke not once that I haue done any goodneſſe, nor ſet my truſt or confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:22575:84"/>vpon them, nor doe exalt my ſelf for them, nor perſwade my ſelfe that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are not able to doe the like or better, nor doe deſire that any man ſhold praiſe mee, although I ſhould ſeem to haue done great wonders: but hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly I do thanke the Lord, that it hath pleaſed his goodneſſe to giue and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow vpon me this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, wiſedome, &amp; grace, to doe this for the loue of him: and thinke, becauſe God hath granted me the grace for to do this there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hath made me more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden vnto him, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore am altogether vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing that any ſhoulde doe otherwiſe but laude &amp; praiſe God for it. And as
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:22575:85"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning my ſelf, I deſire nothing but pain and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile till my laſt end, and that my Lorde God may receiue thereof, the prayſe and thanks, &amp; my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour the gaine and profit: And therfore I deſire no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for all my doinges, becauſe I knowe that I meryte nor deſerue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. Praying God one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that it may pleaſe him to graunt me his loue, that thereby I might bee the more vertuous in all my actions, for neuer to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend him, and that it may pleaſe him to be vnto mee a fauourable and merciful God in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houre of death: as I hope and faithfully put my truſt in him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <pb n="161" facs="tcp:22575:85"/>
               <head>The two and twentith Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter intreateth of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eſire</hi> taking leaue of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Obedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> went his wayes, being great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly comforted by her: and his guide brought him to another of Lady <hi>Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> daughters chamber, called <hi>Chaſtitie,</hi> who like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe entertayned him moſt frendly, and bad him to ſit downe. Wherevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Deſire</hi> did aſke her name, and of what nature and conditions ſhee was. I am quoth ſhee, one of <hi>Humilities</hi> daughters, and
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:22575:86"/>I haue two maide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendant vppon mee, the firſt called <hi>Continency,</hi> the ſeconde <hi>Shametaſtnes,</hi> and my name is called the <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour of the hart.</hi> Who hath likewiſe a daughter ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named the <hi>keeper of the ſences.</hi> I pray you quoth <hi>Deſire</hi> to ſhowe mee this maiden, willingly quoth ſhe, her own name is <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginity. Deſire</hi> did greatly maruaile at the coſtly and ſtraunge apparell of the maid. For firſt of all ſhee held a bridle in her hande, a ſtone and a white lawne with a chaine and a pad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke therevnto. And <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire</hi> ſaid, I pray you ſiſter to let mee vnderſtande what all theſe thinges do meane. This bridle, quoth
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:22575:86"/>ſhee ſerueth for to came a wild beaſt, and although it is very ſmall, yet trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth vs not a little: For if it ſlips once away, it thro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth euery one of vs downe, and there is none then that can rule it, but our Porter called <hi>The fear of God.</hi> Now do you cal this wilde beaſt, ſaid <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire.</hi> It is called anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſhe, the <hi>tongue.</hi> And what doe you with this ſtone demaunded <hi>Deſire:</hi> This ſtone ſerueth quoth ſhee, to ſtoppe vp a gappe which is in our houſe, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>the eares,</hi> for to keepe out theeues, that they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not through it as they doe many times. Some times I doe put it in my mouth, becauſe I
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:22575:87"/>ſhoulde not ſpeake, for it greatly pleaſed the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> ſometimes to refrain his ſpeech. What ſeruice quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> doth the <hi>Loue of God</hi> receiue of you by thus doing? Great ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice anſwered ſhee, for by this dore one looſeth theſe two precious ſtones whereof Ladye <hi>Sinceritie</hi> hath ſpoken of before: And wherto ſerueth this white lawne, quoth <hi>Deſire.</hi> To ſtoppe vp the left eye, ſayd ſhe, and it is called <hi>Hate of Vncleannes.</hi> And do you not couer your right eye, demanded <hi>Deſire,</hi> no ſaide ſhe, for it belongeth to <hi>Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie,</hi> who doth beautifie it with al manner of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and vertuouſneſſe. But this left eye which
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:22575:87"/>ſerueth <hi>Senſualitie,</hi> hath a very ſharpe ſight, and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth any thing ſooner then the right eye, and doth vs much hurte, for it cauſeth death: and therefore it is neceſſary that it ſhould be couered with this lawne, to the end wee might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, and ſee in all things with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> purenes of minde, for to become edified ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, to the honour &amp; praiſe of God, and to the edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our brother. But to what vſe ſerueth this chaine with a padlocke hanging at it. This chain is called, quoth ſhe, <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ocrity,</hi> and ſerueth to chain vp our doores, for to keep out theeues, and likewiſe to keepe all in good order in the houſe, if it were not
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:22575:88"/>for this locke and chayne, we ſhoulde haue no order in any thing, but a confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which ſhould cauſe &amp; procure our deſtruction &amp; ouerthrow.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>The three &amp; twentith chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is a concluſion of the firſt book.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen <hi>Deſire</hi> had beene a while in <hi>Chaſtityes</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, at the laſt taking his leaue of her, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> humble thanks, being likewiſe greatly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted by her words. And his guide leading hun out of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> houſe, ſaide vnto him, nowe thou haſt ſeene all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> houſe, &amp; the Ladies there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:22575:88"/>dwelling, and whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer thou doeſt remember al that thou haſt ſeene and heard here amongſt vs, &amp; put it diligently in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and practiſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haſt enough to finde out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Loue of God.</hi> But yet I wil ſhew th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> a tree which ſtandeth in our Barden. <hi>Deſire</hi> being come into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Garden and hauing ſeene the tree, did maruel great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at the beautie thereof, &amp; chiefly becauſe hee carried two ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry ſorts of fruits, inquiring what they were for fruites: the fruites which growe vppon the loweſt boughs quoth ſhe, which are thus pale and without colour, as thou ſeeſt, are called <hi>Diſcoufi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in himſelfe,</hi> and thoſe
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:22575:89"/>that grow vpon the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt branches, which haue a golden and vermilio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hue, are called <hi>Confidence in God,</hi> and this is the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt fruite that thoſe muſt feede vpon, who do reſort hither. And if they eat not hereof, all their labour is loſt, and in vaine is their comming into this place. will you not giue me ſom of theſe fruites towardes my iourney, quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> moſt willingly quoth ſhe, but firſt fill thy bellie with the fruites of the loweſt boughes, and then thy pockette and ſleeues with thoſe that grow vpon the higheſt brannches, to eate them by the way, til thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meſt into the Pallace of the <hi>Loue of God. Deſire</hi>
                  <pb n="169" facs="tcp:22575:89"/>was glad that hee had ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo good a ſtomacke of the lower fruites, and had filled his bellie with them, and afterwarde did fil his ſleeues, boſome and pockette with the higheſt fruites, and ſaide vnto the Dainſel: I pray you ſhew me the neereſt and readieſt way, which I muſt keepe for to finde out the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> I am glad quoth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Damſell, that I ſee thee thus well furniſhed, and prouided for thy iourney, going to ſeek out the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> yet I feare mee, if thou ſhouldeſt go alone, that thou ſhouldeſt not finde the right way, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will appoint thee ſome good company that ſhall conducte and bring
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:22575:90"/>thee in ſafetie to thy iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies ende. Nowe, quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> haue I not compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye ſufficient enough of my dog? called <hi>Good Will,</hi> No, ſaid ſhee, hee woulde not ſuffice although hee were twice better then he is. For in the way there are not only a great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of theeues, murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and robbers, who ſeaſe vppon men and rob them, but alſo many wild beaſtes, who doo altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther denour them, if they doe catch them: therefore it is good not to truſt too much vpon thy dog See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is ſo, quoth hee, as you ſay: ſhew me ſo much fauour as to appoint mee ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany as you thinke to be needeful and meet for
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:22575:90"/>me. Lake therefore ſaid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhe, the Porter with thee called the <hi>Feare of God,</hi> for he is a ſtrong and valiant man. And if thou wilt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he forſakes thee not, make much of his daughter cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Shamefaſtnes.</hi> And like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe if thou wilt not looſe her, keepe this ſweet pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der alwayes about thee, called <hi>Looke downe warde,</hi> for ſhe delighteth greatly in the ſmell thereof. And the other whom I do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point thee, is <hi>ſinceritie.</hi> And ſo the Lorde bee with thee, and haue thee in his keeping. But before thou goeſt, I muſt admoniſh &amp; inſtruct thee of one thing, which is, if peraduenture thou ſhouldſt com to leeſe the <hi>Feare of God</hi> and <hi>ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie,</hi>
                  <pb n="172" facs="tcp:22575:91"/>at the leaſt look well to thy Dogge, for he ſhall find them out againe, and looke that thou feede hun well with thoſe fruites which thou haſt in thy pocket &amp; about thee. And when thou goeſt hence take the waye which lieth on the left hand, and there ſhalt thou find a foot path which is a great deale noe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer then the high way, &amp; will directly bring thee to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pallace of Loue, where the <hi>Loue of God</hi> dwelleth. How is this footpath cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> that I might inquire of it, If I hapned to miſſe the way, and come in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right path againe. It is called ſaid ſhe, <hi>Patience,</hi> which is the neareſt way to the Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:22575:91"/>of <hi>Humilitie,</hi> and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to that of the <hi>Loue of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <head>The ſecond part of the <hi>Treaſure of the Soule.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>The firſt Chapter intreateth of Patience.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eſire</hi> parted merely fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the pallace of <hi>Humility,</hi> hauing fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the ſru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tes of the Garden thereof, and was
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:22575:92"/>well prouided with good companie, namely, with his Dogge <hi>Good-wil.</hi> And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his one ſide with the <hi>Feare of God,</hi> and at the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with <hi>ſincetitie,</hi> and his pockets full beſides, with the fruites of <hi>To truſt in God.</hi> And although they had tolde him that it was ſhorter and a great deale neerer then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther waye, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, did find it to be very harde and tedious, ful of ſtones, hedges and thornes. Where vpon hee ſaid to <hi>ſincerity,</hi> O good God how coms this way ſo harde, vneaſie and todi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, I neuer would haue thought it, that it coulde haue beene ſo. Marua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le not, qd <hi>ſinceritie,</hi> for there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:22575:92"/>it is called the way of <hi>Patience:</hi> and if it were not ſo ful of ſtones, prick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les and thornes, and not ſo troubleſome to walke in it, it ſhould not beare the name, which it doeth, and the houſe where it bringeth a man vnto, not of ſuch a great eſtimation, if the way were euen and pleaſant, and euery one could walk in it according to his owne will and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king. But nowe none come thether before they be firſt well exerciſed in vertue. For doſt thou not remember the common prouerbe. <hi>There is no gaine without paine, No ioy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out annoy.</hi> And ſeeing thou art now entred into it, bee of good cheere, for
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:22575:93"/>it will not laſt long: for thou knoweſt that be who deſireth to fiſh, muſt not feare the water: and doeſt thou thinke then to finde ſo coſtly and precious a treaſure as is the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> without paine? Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member I pray thee, what Seneca ſaith, A rare and precious thing is not to bee bought with ſmal mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: Beſided, the ende of toyle and labour, is reſt &amp; quiet. Therefore it were a fooliſh thing but once to imagine that ſuch a coſtly iewell could bee gotten ſo eaſily at euery mans plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. For if one could find the <hi>Loue of God</hi> ſo lightly, he wold be nothing eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of, becauſe lightly gotten lightly forgotten.
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:22575:93"/>Therefore do thy beſt, and let a ſmall paine not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noy thee, then afterward thou ſhalt reſt with the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> reioyce, and dayly banket with him: and the greater pain thou takeſt now to finde him, the more wilt thou eſteem of him, and with greater diligence wilt thou ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour thy ſelfe to keepe his fauour. And likewiſe how thy paine &amp; trauell which thou haſt taken for him, hath beene more tedious, ſo much the greater ſhall bee thy ioy, comforte and pleaſure. Againe if thou feeleſt thy ſelfe weake and almoſt ready to ſounde, take a little of the fruit, <hi>To truſt in God,</hi> which thou haſt about thee, and it wil
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:22575:94"/>reniue thee againe. And if thou wilt not feele the tediouſnes of the way, do as commonly all trauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers do, who with a ſong doe lighten the tediouſnes of their iourney. <hi>Sinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> wordes did pleaſe <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire,</hi> and ſaide: howe is it poſſible that one ſhoulde ſing in this olde mans company, for commonly age is alwaies repugnant to youthful actions. It is his cuſtome quoth ſhee to beare ſuch graue and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere a countenance, but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe hee is very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt, frendly, and merry, for he is the <hi>Loue of Gods</hi> onely brother, and deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in mirth, but chiefly when we ſing no vayne, light, or worldly ſonges.
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:22575:94"/>How ſhall I beginne to ſing, quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> ſeeing I haue no voice at all? It cannot be, anſwered <hi>Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie,</hi> that thou ſhouldeſt not haue any voice, ſeeing that thou thy ſelfe art a voyce. <hi>Deſire</hi> did maruel, becauſe ſhe ſaide, that hee was a voice himſelfe, and aſkt howe it was poſſible that it ſhould be ſo. Thou and all creatures, quoth ſhee, art created by the word of God, &amp; it is moſt manifeſt, that ſoone after the worde vttered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> voice followed. And ſeeing that as ſoone as the Lorde had ſpoken the word, all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures were made and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated: it followeth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that all creatures are voyces. I pray you quoth
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:22575:95"/>
                  <hi>Deſire,</hi> to tel me this ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more plainer that I might conceiue it. Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly anſwered <hi>Sincerity.</hi> The ſpeech and the word is all one thing, for the ſpeech is not that, which is vttered by the mouth, but it is the conceite of the mind, &amp; that which man ſpeaketh with the mouth is the voyce, which vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth and giueth to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the ſpeech, the word, and the inwarde conceite of the mind. As for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: When I doe thinke with my ſelfe, that thou art a man, this is a word or ſpeech, although it ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth hidden w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in me. Now let vs heare, quoth <hi>Deſire</hi> ſeeing that I am a voice, what kind of voice am I?
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:22575:95"/>Thou art, anſwered <hi>Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity,</hi> a voice of the Lord, who hath created thee to honour, laude and praiſe him. But what doe I ſay of my ſelfe (as I am a voice) qd <hi>Deſire,</hi> through the good which thou haſt receiued from God, ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de ſhe, thou crieſt that God is good and bountifull, &amp; by the comelines where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he hath endued thee, thou ſayeſt that God is beautifull: and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wherewith God hath endued thee, is but a voice of him, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his bounty &amp; good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. What reaſon haue you qd <hi>Deſire,</hi> to ſay that all wherewith God hath adorned me, is but a voice of him, &amp; ſayeſt not gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally,
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:22575:96"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="181" facs="tcp:22575:96"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="182" facs="tcp:22575:97"/>that all which I haue in mee is his voyce? Becauſe anſwered ſhe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſin and wickednes, which do remain in thee, are not created of God, &amp; therfore they cannot hee voyces of the Lorde, but well thine owne, declaring that thou art vile, wicked, defiled &amp; vncleane, for as man may come by the creatures, to the knowledge of God, ſo likewiſe may hee attaine through the workes, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from himſelf to his own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="183" facs="tcp:22575:97"/>
               <head>The ſecond Chapter decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the knowledge of God through his c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>atures.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eſire</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed as the Ladies graue cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce. I althogh the ſeemed to bee but plaine, was notwithſtanding ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſkilfull and learned in all heauenly knowledge, and ſaid vnto her, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore woulde you haue vs to ſing? Therefore quoth ſhee, becauſe wee might hereby ſomewhat forget the tediouſnes and paine of this vale of miſerye: wherevnto the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:22575:98"/>and contemplatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Gods creatures, is likewiſe a great aide and furtherance, and therefore haue I placed them in the way of <hi>Patience,</hi> for the ſooner ſhalt thou come to the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> if thou do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt exerciſe thy hart often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in the booke of the creation: for through <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience</hi> and the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, (whereof all the world is but a booke) we attaine to the knowledge of God, and are greatly comforted in a diſtreſſed hope. And if thou wilt learne to tune thy voyce, learne it of the creatures, for ſome of them declare his goodnes, ſome ſhewe his might, ſome his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome, ſome his excellency,
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:22575:98"/>ſome his beauty, ſome his mercy, ſome his bountie, and generally all more or leſſe ſounde forth his om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotency, that all in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration hereof ſhoulde ſpread abroade his prayſe and glorie. Therefore endeuour thy ſelf to learn to ſing here by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way, for where thou goeſt, namely in the pallace of the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> they doe nothing but ſinge forth his praiſe. Teach me I pray you, quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> to ſing by his creatures, for I cannot learne it of my ſelf, willingly, anſwered <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity.</hi> In the mean while <hi>Deſire</hi> trauelled farre and wide in this deſart, where he ſaw many great won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Lord, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:22575:99"/>to learne and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue his mercie and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp; moſt part through <hi>Sincerities</hi> helpe, doctrine and teaching: yet he was forced to endure and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine many dangers, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilles and paine, for he did ſtumble oftentimes, but <hi>Sinceritie</hi> kept him from falling, and yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſometimes fell, but <hi>ſincerity</hi> did reach him the hande, and holpe him vp againe, and ſometimes catcht ſuch falles, that if the <hi>Feare of God</hi> had not aided him, he neuer wold or could haue riſen again, ſometimes when he ſhold go forwardes, went back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, &amp; when he ſhould haue amended himſelfe by the creatures, oftentimes
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:22575:99"/>did greatly hinder himſelf thereby. For hee did not endeuour to learne their ſecret voyces, but became hoarſe throgh negligence and ſlothfulnes, vntill the feare of God gaue hun a good puſh, and driue him forwardes. Oftentimes he did treade on a thorne, but <hi>ſincerity</hi> incc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uted his feete and drew him out of it againe. Oftentimes fell a ſleepe, but the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eare of God</hi> did awake him: ſometimes being wearie, ſate down and reſted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but his dogge <hi>Good-will</hi> did not holde off from barking, vntill he did riſe againe. Sometimes the way was ſo tedious vnto him, that his heart began to faint <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>un, and deſired
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:22575:100"/>to turne backe againe, but as ſoone as he did eate of the fruites <hi>to truſt in God,</hi> which hee had in his poc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, and in euery place a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him, came to himſelf and waxed ſtrong againe. And ſometimes going by night, loſt the <hi>feare of God</hi> and <hi>ſinceritie,</hi> ſo that hee miſt his way, but as ſoone as the day appeared, and the Sun began to ſhine, found quickly the way a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine by meanes of his dogge. And when they had thus trauailed certain daies, came at the laſt into a faire large and pleaſant field, in the midſt whereof ſtood a princely and coaſtly pallace, called <hi>Loue,</hi> where the <hi>Loue of God</hi> was por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <pb n="189" facs="tcp:22575:100"/>
            <head>THE THIRDE parte of the Treaſure <hi>of the Soule.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Of Loue &amp; Charity.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>The firſt Chapter doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat howe the Loue of God doth exerciſe and trie vs.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DEſire</hi> was glad whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſawe ſo faire and princely a pallace, &amp; founde by experience that this wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſome, tedious, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome way had ſo good &amp; pleaſant an iſſue. Came
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:22575:101"/>therefore preſently at the gates of the pallace, but finding them ſhutte cloſe, begun to call and knocke, yet notwithſtanding after long crying and knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, none came to aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere. Call and crie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loude, quoth <hi>ſincerity,</hi> for in ſo doing, although they were all a ſleepe, or halfe deafe, it cannot be but they ſhal heare thee. Knocke harde with the hammers which do hang at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gates, and then ſoone they will open the doores vnto thee (for there hung two ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers at the gate called <hi>to ſigh and weepe.</hi> Knocke, harde and boldly, quoth ſhe, for if they were not wont to open the gate to none, theſe two hammers
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:22575:101"/>ſhoulde not hange at the doore, for I thinke they are made for that purpoſe, to let all thoſe in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> knocke with them. <hi>Deſire</hi> hauing knockt and called very long before the <hi>Loue of God</hi> wold open the gates was yet at y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> laſt comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by his comming, who hauing opened the doore, <hi>Deſire</hi> knewe him not. Brother, quoth the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> what doeſt thou lack or deſire? For whom doſt thou look here? Thou art wearie perhappes to haue watched ſo longe at the gate, and to haue knocked ſo oftentimes. But here wee fame vs all to be halfe deafe, to trie y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> conſtancie and patience of trauellers who come he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:22575:102"/>And when we find ſome that are wearie, and perſwade themſelues that there is nothing els be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing vnto it, but as ſoone as they are come, then preſently to open the gates for them, and let them come in: then wee let thoſe without opening vnto them, returne backe againe, becauſe wee open not the dore to any who thinketh that hee hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued it, and perſwades himſelfe that he is worthy of it, and that it is our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and are bound to doe it. And art thou none of thoſe fellowes? No, my good Lorde, quoth <hi>Deſire.</hi> For although I haue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered and ſuſtained much ſorrow and paine both of
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:22575:102"/>bodie and ſoule, yet I know for certaine, that I haue not deſerued, &amp; am altogether vnworthye to enter into the houſe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it woulde pleaſe your Lord ſhippe through your great mercye &amp; goodnes, to leade and bring mee within. wherefore woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thou come in quoth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Loue of God,</hi> or whome doeſt thou ſeeke heere in this houſe? My Lorde aunſwered <hi>Deſire,</hi> I am come from the Pallace of <hi>Humilitie,</hi> accompanied w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe worthy perſonages. and haue taken my tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney through the neereſt waye being <hi>Patience,</hi> to ſeeke out the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> who as I am informed, keepeth here his reſidence.
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:22575:103"/>Doeſt thou not bring any token, quoth the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> whereby a man may know thou commeſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence? Yea my Lord, ſaid <hi>Deſire,</hi> I haue broght true tokens with me, whereof the one was giuen mee in the houſe of <hi>Humilitie,</hi> and is called <hi>Knowledge of him ſelfe,</hi> and the other haue I learned by the way, and is called <hi>Knowledge of God.</hi> I am glad, quoth the <hi>Loue God,</hi> to ſee thee ſo wel pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, but doſt thou think that for this knowledge ſake we are bounde to let thee enter here? No my Lorde, aunſwered <hi>Deſire,</hi> but onely as I haue ſaide before, for thy grace and mercies ſake, becauſe I cannot tell whether theſe
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:22575:103"/>two ſundrie knowledges are perfecte or not, and therefore I doubt of their ſufficiency, I knowe that I haue dwelt in the Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of <hi>Humility</hi> for a time, and that they haue ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me there all the houſe, the Damſels, their nature and condition, but I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell whether I haue well digeſted in my ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke the fruites which I haue eaten there, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they were vnto mee very toothſome and pleaſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>des, I doe not know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> wherther I haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kelle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ornes haue gri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y hurt me, &amp; my com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ue hath brought me hether almoſt perforce.
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:22575:104"/>Therefore my good Lord, I can aſſure thee of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that I bring with me, but onely of my wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, vnbelief, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection. And the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt occaſion that moued mee to ſeeke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Loue of God</hi> was this, that I hearde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was a good Phiſition and Chirurgion, &amp; would let mee blonde and purge mee from all corruptions and vncleanneſſe: And I am tolde, as ſoone as hee doth ſee one, knoweth pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly his diſeaſe, although it lyeth hidden ſecreat win the hearte. And whereſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hee putteth his hande vpon, there hee purgeth and cleanſeth all thinges. Wherefore ſaid the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> doeſt thou deſire to
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:22575:104"/>be thus cleane, ſound, and vnſpotted? Becauſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered <hi>Deſire,</hi> that I was alſo tolde, that none who were vncleane and vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed, ſhould or could en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or come into this place. Seeing it is ſo, as thou ſayeſt quoth the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> and that thou put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt all thy confidence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our handes, tarrie here a while, for thou canſt not become familiar with the <hi>loue of God,</hi> ere thou become acquainted firſt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his page, therefore I will go call him, and hee will inſtruct thee of all what thou haſt to do, and ſpeak vnto his Lorde and mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="198" facs="tcp:22575:105"/>
               <head>The ſecond Chapter intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of the loue of his neighbour.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eſire</hi> tarried w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forth comminge of this Page, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he might bring him to the ſpeech of his Lorde and maiſter, And not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſawe him come, and was called <hi>Neighbourly loue,</hi> which ſight did great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly reioyce him, that euen for the loue which he bare to ſhe <hi>Loue of God,</hi> coulde not abſtaine fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> weeping. Wherefore doſt thou weep quoth <hi>Neighbourly loue,</hi> for they are all merrie in this houſe, &amp; from hence
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:22575:105"/>is baniſhed all ſorrowe &amp; ladneſſe. I do not weepe for any griefe, ſaid <hi>Deſire,</hi> but for ioy. For whome doſt thou ſeek here, quoth <hi>Neighbourly loue.</hi> My ſon, anſwered he, I looke for the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> I am his ſeruant &amp; page, quoth he, and if thou doeſt ſeeke my Lorde, firſt of all thou muſt ſpeake and come ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with me, for my Lorde loueth me deerely, &amp; therefore thoſe that loue not me, he wil not know them, nor once ſpeake vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them. Faine would I know thy nature &amp; condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> &amp; for thy Lorde and mayſters ſake become acquainted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thee? If thou doeſt deſire my acquaintance &amp; frend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe,
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:22575:106"/>quoth <hi>Neighbourly loue,</hi> thou muſt prouide &amp; giue mee euery morninge an hearb for my breakfaſt, called <hi>to thinke humblie,</hi> &amp; for my dinner another, called <hi>to ſpeake humblie,</hi> &amp; for my ſupper another not vnlike the firſt, called <hi>to worke and doe humblie.</hi> But where ſhall I get theſe hearbes, quoth <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire,</hi> the firſt called to <hi>think humblie,</hi> aunſwered the Page, groweth in <hi>Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities</hi> garden, where ſhe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed her ſelfe a ſlaue of all ſlaues, and worſe then a beaſt. But to come ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily to this hearbe, becauſe it is a great way to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of <hi>Humilitie,</hi> and thou ſhalt take a horſe to ride on, called <hi>to thinke well of
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:22575:106"/>euerie man,</hi> and by theſe means mayeſt thou come by this hearb euery mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. The ſecond hearbe is made of three ſundrye hearbes, of the firſt <hi>thinke humblie,</hi> of <hi>meekenes</hi> and <hi>affabilitie in ſpeech,</hi> &amp; vpon the laſt is caſt a ſmal pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der called <hi>Slow</hi> and <hi>little.</hi> The third hearbe called <hi>to worke humblie,</hi> is made of diuers hearbes, whereof <hi>Mirth, loue,</hi> and <hi>quietneſſe</hi> or <hi>dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</hi> are the chiefeſt. And whenſoeuer thou doeſt feede mee with theſe hearbs, then our acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and frend ſhippe wil co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue &amp; abide for euer, &amp; I wil ſoons bring thee to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpeech of my maiſter. The counſell and doctrine of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Page did delight <hi>Deſire,</hi> &amp;
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:22575:107"/>ſaid: Seeing thou haſt made me acquainted with thy nature and deſire, I will diligently endeuour my ſelf to procure and get theſe hearbes, for to giue them vnto thee. After this they both continued in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliaritie one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a long time. And <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire</hi> hauing conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t time and opportunitie, ſaid vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, I beſeech thee ſhew me ſo much fauour, as to bringe mee to thy Lorde. Willingly, quoth <hi>Neighbourly loue,</hi> for thou haſt done thine endeuour ſince thou haſt beene with mee. But tarrie here a while, I will go call my Lorde, &amp; ſee whether hee will come forth to ſpeake with thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="203" facs="tcp:22575:107"/>
               <head>The thirde Chapter intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of the loue of God &amp; his neighbour, and of the ſecond degree to loue, &amp; of his office, and dayly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eſire</hi> doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whether the <hi>Loue of God</hi> woulde come forth to ſpeake with him, becauſe he ſaw his own vileneſſe, pouertie, and miſerie, and how vnworthy he was to ſpeake with ſuch a Lorde, eſpied one to come to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes him: who ſaide, Brother, what doeſt thou looke for, or what is thy deſire? Sir quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> I looke for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Loue of God.</hi>
                  <pb n="204" facs="tcp:22575:108"/>I am bee, aunſwered the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> And as ſoone as <hi>Deſire</hi> did heare this, fell in a ſounde, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Loue of God</hi> tooke him by the hand, and lifting him vp, reuiued him againe. And when hee ſawe the <hi>loue of God</hi> make ſo much of him, hee began moſt bitterly to weepe, inſomuch that hee could not ſpeak any word at all. Which the <hi>loue of God</hi> ſeeing, being of a ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and tender heart, was moued with compaſſion, and meruailed greatly of the extreame loue, deſire &amp; affection which <hi>Deſire</hi> did beare vnto him, becauſe he ſaw him weep for very ioy: and ſaid, I pray thee weepe no more, and doe not make me ſadde, for I
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:22575:108"/>cannot abide to ſee thoſe weepe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> loue mee. Tell me who told thee I dwelt here? A ſhepheard, quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> whome I met by the way, and did direct me hether. What ſaid he of me vnto thee, ſaid the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> that thou loueſt and deſireſt me ſo much: doeſt thou loue mee ſo deerely, becauſe thou haſt beene told, that I am bountiful to my frendes, and vnto thoſe that ſerue mee, very franke and liberall? No quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> not therfore, but becauſe you are a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and good Lorde, and becauſe you bring your frendes in a place where they ſhall ſee God, which is the greateſt bleſſedneſſe of at the world. This good
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:22575:109"/>and holy minde of <hi>Deſire</hi> did delight y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Loue of God</hi> not a little, &amp; was an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion that he loued him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more for it, I meruell my Lord, quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> ſeeing your highnes are ſo noble a Prince<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that your Grace putteth thoſe that come to ſeeke you to ſuch pain and trauaile, and are ſo hardly so be found out. Hold thy peace, anſwered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Loue of God,</hi> this miſterie is hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den from many. For ſome there are, who thinke they haue not founde mee, nor knowen me, yet I now<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting am alwaies neere them, and they are filled and repleniſhed with me. And ſome there are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe who perſwade them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue founds
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:22575:109"/>me, who are yet far from me, and know me not. I pray your highnes thee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> to let me vnderſtande your na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and conditions, that I may know thereby whether I am neer or far from you, for I take you for my Lorde and maiſter. Mine exerciſe and office is, aunſwered the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> to loue God, &amp; I am a child of <hi>the knowledge of God.</hi> In what ſort do you loue God, quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> I haue aunſwered the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> a deſire to wiſh for him with all my heart, &amp; with all the ſtrength and force of my ſoule, and to find him I leaue nothing vndone, vſing all means thereunto poſſible. And
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:22575:110"/>that I might knowe him the better, to his praiſe &amp; glorie. I deſire that all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth wold acknowledge his vnſpeakeable and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite goodneſſe, and that all creatures ſhould laud, honour and praiſe him. with this deſire I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine and force my ſelfe to do nothing wherewith to diſpleaſe him: and if peraduenture I offend him, then preſently I proſtrate my ſelfe before him, and craue pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at his hands for my offence: and then we are as good frendes as euer wee were before: and becauſe my Lord and God is ſo bountifull and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ood, I am not yet coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed to this firſt degree, but
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:22575:110"/>I endeuour my ſelfe alſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to my ſmall power a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e to execute and doe that which he or any of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> leaſt amongſt vs doeth command mee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with as great diligence as may be. And hereby onely I can perceiue howe dearely I do loue him, when I doe that which he commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth me. For certainly I beleeue that nothing is more acceptable or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant vnto him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> no ſeruice or reuerence more delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful then the obedience vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to his will and comman<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dementes. For he him ſelf doth ſay, how can thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice pleaſe mee, or howe canſt thou perſwade thy ſelt that I loue thee, when thou doeſt not keepe my
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:22575:111"/>commandementes. For knowe that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that ioyned &amp; knit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted faſter thy ſpirite with thine, then willingly to execute my will, and keep my lawes and ſtatutes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>The fourth Chapter doeth proſecute the office of the loue of God in the ſame degree.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gree of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, I haue purpoſed to do al thinges, where unto by office and calling I am bound unto: and ſeeing that I haue nowe bounde my ſelfe to God, (whereof I repent
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:22575:111"/>me not) I am willing to obey his will and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement. Daily there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I conſider my office, and all thinges there vnto belonging, and for the better execution hereof, I diligently follow the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of the godly, and the holy Scriptures, for I know that many herein offende my Lord, becauſe they are ignorant of thoſe things, which are belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their dutie. And if they knowe it, and doe it not, then they are farre worſe, becauſe they ſinne not through ignoraunce, or weakeneſſe, but onely through meere wilfulnes and mallice. Beſides that, which I haue promiſed and haue ſworne, &amp; vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:22575:112"/>vnto him, (wherevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to I am moſt bounde) I endeuour w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all diligence to performe and keepe it. Therefore I haue vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto my Lorde to ſerue him with three dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelles, <hi>Obedience, Chaſtity,</hi> and <hi>Pouertie.</hi> Therefore euery morning, I ſtudy how I might beſt ſerue &amp; pleaſe him, ſpeaking vnto my ſoule as followeth. Let vs caſt about, my ſoule, how we ſhall behaue our ſelues, this day to pleaſe and to ſerue our Lorde, and again in the euening, I ſay vnto her. Let vs ſee O my Soule, howe wee haue ſerued our Lorde to day with the ſaide Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, whether we haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended him in any thing
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:22575:112"/>or no: and in this ſorte I endeuour my ſelfe to bee a loyall ſeruant to my Lorde, with theſe Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelles. Wherefore do you this quoth <hi>Deſire.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore anſwered the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> becauſe theſe three Damſelles are Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines to my Lorde, and none can come in his cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and ſpeake with him: vnleſſe firſt they do open him the doores, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare him the entry. I pray you, quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> to tell me what ſpirituall exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes you do vſe, for to bee faithfull vnto theſe dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, I haue anſwered the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> three intents which I do offer both day and night, that further me to all manner of ſeruice.
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:22575:113"/>The firſt intent is called <hi>Wiſh or aduance not.</hi> The ſeconde, <hi>Deſire nothing.</hi> The firſt intent ſerueth <hi>Obedience,</hi> when I dreſſe it with a certaine ſauſe, called <hi>to doe,</hi> and then is called <hi>Aduance not to doe,</hi> And the finer I dreſſe this for her diet, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more frend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe ſhe getteth for me, and in greater fauour ſhe bringers me w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my Lorde, and ſayeth much good of me vnto him, ſo that he by her words loues me dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and is a mercifull and bountifull Lord unto me. This foreſaid diſh, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Aduance not to do,</hi> when I dreſſe it with another ſauſe called <hi>to haue,</hi> then it is called, <hi>Wiſh or aduance not to haue,</hi> &amp; herewithal
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:22575:113"/>I feede and maintaine the other Damſell called <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty.</hi> Stay a while quoth <hi>Deſire.</hi> Why ſhoulde I not wiſh or aduance my ſelfe, to haue ſomething when I lacke? This is not thus to be underſtoode, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> for if thou needeſt ſome thing, thou haſt thy Soueraign, who wil by himſelfe, or by his commanders ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently prouided for thee, without thy wiſhinge or asking, which is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnmannerly. For where one is, who hath the commaundement, and care ouer all the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold, hee will ſufficiently prouide for them all, after his power &amp; abilitie, &amp; as
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:22575:114"/>it becommeth his duetie, place, and authoritie. To the end the reſt ſhould addict themſelues more ze<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>louſly to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeruice of God and to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contemplation of heauenly and ſpirituall thinges, without euery mans owne and perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar carefulnes, to craue, aſke or aduance to haue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which he needeth. And it were a greate ouerſight that a chiefe commaunder of anye place ſhould not haue the care and forecaſt to prouide for his ſubiects or houſh oldes neceſſitie, without their asking. But that which I ſpeake of aduancing, demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or crauing, is diuerſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but chiefely two waies
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:22575:114"/>to be vnderſtode. Firſt when they prouide not for thy neceſſitie without thy aſking or crauing, which is greatly to be miſliked, diſcommended &amp; diſpraiſed in a congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whatſoeuer. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that which thou needeſt thou doeſt lacke it gretly, and not to be wilfull and wanton. Orels in all thinges which thou canſt deſire, therin will conſiſt curioſitie, ſuperfluitie and tempting of God. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue me that vnder the couer &amp; colour of neceſſitie, lie oftentimes hidden di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and many ſinnes, &amp; chieflie in things belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the maintenance &amp; and ſuſtenance of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as meare, drinke, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:22575:115"/>and ſuch like things are. How ſhall I know quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> whether it be needfull, ſuperfluitie or wantonneſſe onely, that which I demand or craue to haue. See anſwered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>loue of God,</hi> whether thou canſt forbeare it, and liue without it, without the great hinderaunce, perill and daunger of thy ſoule and body. But if thou didſt perceiue that it ſhold turne thee to ſuch perill &amp; damage, then to <hi>Deſire no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> were a great ſinne and madneſſe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes. But if thou canſt forbeare it and bee without it, ſo it bee not as I haue ſayde daungerous, and hurte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:22575:115"/>to thy health, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſomewhat paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, troubleſome and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious to thy fleſhe, then to <hi>Deſire nothing</hi> is a great vertue, and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of prayſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation. But as the holy Scripture ſayeth: Bleſſed is the man that ſuffereth ſomething for the <hi>Loue of GOD.</hi> Therefore if thou canſt forbear it without the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarding, and indangering both of thy ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, then to craue, aske, and demande, eſteeme it wantonneſſe onely, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it couereth it ſelfe w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> the cloake of neceſſity, want, need, &amp; holines. For ſinnes neuer diſcloſe and ſhewe themſelues hare,
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:22575:116"/>but preſent themſelues al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies vnder the colour of good thinges, and hereby mayeſt thou know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be neceſſarie or not when thou craueſt ſome thing,</p>
               <p>And that none deceiue themſelues in their owne opinion, they need great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a diligent inquiſition, &amp; a vertuous exerciſe, and if they be deſtitute hereof, then ſet them goe about their buſineſſe with coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of the holy ſcriptures, or with the aduice of a gooly and wiſe man, who will inſtruct them herein,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="221" facs="tcp:22575:116"/>
               <head>The fifte Chapter intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of the two other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes, namely of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire nothing, and reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeinge I haue nowe diſcloſed vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to thee my firſt intent, wherewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all I maintayne the two damoſels <hi>Obedience</hi> and <hi>Pouertie</hi> likewiſe I will diſcouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nature and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie of others, namely <hi>Deſire nothing,</hi> &amp; <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber nothing.</hi> Thou muſt know that the ſaid firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, <hi>To wiſhe for nothing,</hi>
                  <pb n="222" facs="tcp:22575:117"/>grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and commeth of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but from a <hi>Deſire to haue or doe nothing.</hi> And when the cauſe which is the <hi>Deſire, to wiſhe for,</hi> is taken awaye and rooted out, then his force and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect doth ceaſe quickly, which is, <hi>To aske for.</hi> And hereby is made y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is contrarie to it, namely <hi>To aske nothing,</hi> which is my ſecond intent, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall I maintain dame Pouertie. But thou muſt marke, that this <hi>Deſire,</hi> is vnderſtood only of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye and earthly matters. But becauſe this hearbe hath an other roote, where out it groweth, which is to <hi>Remember,</hi> (for nothing there can bee wiſht for, which was not before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred)
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:22575:117"/>therefore make much of this third intent, which is, to <hi>Remember no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> wherewithall I mayntain the third Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, called <hi>Chaſtitie.</hi> But y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> muſt vnderſtande this, <hi>Remembring,</hi> when it is ſubſtantiall, ſtedfaſt, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and ſpringing out of a fleſhly luſt. For it is not in mans power not to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member nothing,</hi> but wel not to ſuffer thoughtes to remayne and caſt foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations in him, but to turne them quickly of, and to thinke of God. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that this hearbe <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring</hi> doeth water it ſelfe with a water called <hi>To ſee,</hi> we muſt caſt vpon it a pouder called <hi>Diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to haue care to the eyes,</hi>
                  <pb n="224" facs="tcp:22575:118"/>which is very profitable ſo it.</p>
               <p>Theſe three intents, do not onely clenſe my ſoule of all worldly things, as ſelfe-wil &amp; ſuch like ſpots, but they breede in mee a great purenes &amp; promp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, to loue my Lorde, drawing from me al other loues, and vniting me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together with him. In theſe three intents I haue comprehended all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther godly exerciſes ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the ſpirite, as well of <hi>Humilitie,</hi> as of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vertues, becauſe I know that the perfection of vertue conſiſteth here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. Thinke not therefore that in vame I ſerue theſe three Ladies, for they bee very gracious, and get me
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:22575:118"/>much fauour. One of the three called <hi>Pouerty,</hi> hath giuen me a faire iewell. I pray you quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> to let me ſee it? I keepe it anſwered the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> in two places, namelie, in my heart and Bed-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. This iewel is ſo coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and of ſuch price and value, that I was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to keepe it in my hart, before I had caſt out of it all earthly loue. And in like ſort, it coulde haue no place in my Bed-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, before I had caſt and throwne out of it all curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſuperfluous, and partiall things, reſeruing onely to my vſe, but a few bookes. Now do you call this iewell quoth <hi>Deſire?</hi> It is called, anſwered the
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:22575:119"/>
                  <hi>Loue of God. Nothing at all,</hi> for this is the greateſt treaſure that <hi>Pouertie</hi> can poſſeſſe, who is the richeſt Ladie of all the earth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe hath as much treaſure hereof as ſhe will her ſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="227" facs="tcp:22575:119"/>
               <head>The ſixte Chapter doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the office of the Loue of God, and beſides, intreateth of praier.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rity wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I haue ſpoken, which was for to obey his commaundement (as my duetie doeth require) there is yet another cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance to bee conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, for the Office ſake, wherein hee hath placed me, namely to be his cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlain. Which is, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer I come to ſerue him,
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:22575:120"/>or come to craue ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at his hands, or but onely to ſpeake with him: I haue then a ſpecial care to come before him, with ſuch great humilitie, low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines &amp; pureneſſe of mind as I am able. And the purer and cleaner that my heart is, the more caſie I ſee, beholde and knowe him. And pray my louing brother, the <hi>Feare of God,</hi> and my Aunt <hi>Reuerence,</hi> to keepe mee companye. What do you when Lady <hi>Reuerence</hi> goeth with you ſaid <hi>Deſire.</hi> Then I reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and think what I am, anſwered the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> and ſet before my eyes the maieſty and greatnes of my Lord, who is to be ſerued with feare and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence,
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:22575:120"/>as one onely worthie of it. Beſides, I remember that all An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and heauenly princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities do fall downe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, worſhippe and adore him, being aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, at ſuch great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible a Maieſtie. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer I conclude, that hee knoweth the ſecrets of my bart, and ſeeth my inward thoughtes, better then I my ſelfe. Likewiſe that he can, according vnto his godly will and pleaſure, doo and vndoo all things, and that life and death, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and not being, and the ſaluation and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of al the world are in his hand and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Furthermore, I reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:22575:121"/>that hee is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and welſpring of all goodneſſe, the onely and Soueraigne good in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth: and when diligently I put in minde thoſe thinges, then I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne to ſhake and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, then my hearte and minde beginnes to alter, ſo that oftentimes I fall in a ſound: chieflie when I conſider that I being ſo wicked, vile, vncleane, &amp; worſer then any dog, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to vndertake ſuch an high office, &amp; to be ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch a mighty Lord, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch a renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Maieſty will vouchſafe to delight in my vile com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, &amp; ſuffer me to ſpeak &amp; eat w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him, as his fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar and onely friend. And
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:22575:121"/>oftentimes my ſelfe do tel him of it, ſaying: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doeſt thou ſuffer, O my God, theſe vile &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean ſinners to ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee? How my Lord, is it decent y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou ſhould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt be ſerued of ſuch wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches &amp; wicked offenders as we are? Where is the honour and reuerence due to thy princely Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie? But what aunſwere doeth he giue you, quoth <hi>Deſire.</hi> I cannot tell an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> but onely that for very ioy hee makes mee to weepe, and ſaith: Doo not trouble thy ſelfe herewithall, for y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt not procured thee the office, &amp; haſt not pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced thy ſelfe in it, but I haue called thee vnto it,
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:22575:122"/>and I know wherefore I haue done it, but bee thou carefull to looke to thy calling: and that which thy Office doth require &amp; demaunde: endeuour thy ſelfe diligently to further and performe it. What do you ſay vnto him, quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> when you come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, accompanied w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Humilitie, Charity, Feare,</hi> and <hi>Reuerence.</hi> Firſt of al, quoth the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> when I craue ſomething at his hands, and would moue him to grant me my requeſt, then I endeuour with all my force and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to exalte and prayſe him: and ceaſe not for to giue him thankes for all his benefits which I haue receiued, for I knowe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb n="233" facs="tcp:22575:122"/>this is acceptable &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in his ſight. And whenſoeuer I goe about to praiſe him, then I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe all the wondrous workes which hee hath done, recreating and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting my ſelfe therein greatly. This ſame I do touching his great pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, wiſedome, and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, further I rehearſe his great mercye and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites, which he hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vppon his people and ſeruants, praiſing and magnifying him therein. I doe not forget alſo his great mercy ſhewed vnto his enemies, which hee doeth dayly yet continue, maruelling greatly in his omnipotency, excellencie, &amp; incomprehenſible good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:22575:123"/>in that he doeth not puniſh them according to their deſertes, but rather doeth make them parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of his bountie and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralitie. I thanke him alſo for the great mercye which in him is alwaies reſident, delighting to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count his vertues &amp; beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie which flow and runne from him, prayſing and magnilying him for thoſe, and reioycing in them, &amp; in his vnſpeake able mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. And this I do often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, becauſe I knowe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this is his will, and doeth greatly pleaſe him. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides his will is, that we being familiar with him, ſhould talke of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ecret and heauenly thinges, which are hidden from thoſe that
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:22575:123"/>doe not eſteeme to enter in his priuie Chamber, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they are of his houſholde and dayly ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes. Wherefore, quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> doe you giue him all this praiſe, thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and bleſſing? becauſe anſwered the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> the more I extol his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the more I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and humble my ſelfe before him, the more I am agreeable, and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vnto him. For this is his moſt bleſſed &amp; holy will, that we ſhould haue alwaies before our eyes, his vnſpeakeable good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, highneſſe, excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, &amp; omnipotency, &amp; our weaknes. And although I giue vnto him as much praiſe &amp; thanks as euer I
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:22575:124"/>may, I am certaine, that therein I can bee no lyar, for hee is of greater excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie, power, highneſſe, and worthineſſe, then I or any mortall or unmor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall tongue can vtter, or any heauenly or earthlye creature conceiue or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehende.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>The ſeuenth chapter intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of the loue of God in the ſecond degree, &amp; doth proſecute the manner of prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that I haue prayſed, thanked, and exalted him as much as I am
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:22575:124"/>able, then I do commend vnto him my ſoule, my whole will, and the beſt intent and minde which I haue: which is, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I might gaine all the world, I would in no wiſe anger or offend him, praying him out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of my hearte, that it would pleaſe him to keep, ſtrengthen and further me in this good and godly minde, for without him were I not able to keepe it long. This done, I praye him for the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of all my treſpaſſes, and offences, wherein I haue tranſgreſſed his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly laws, and that he wold not let me ſet my thoghts, loue and minde vpon any thing, but vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him onely.
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:22575:125"/>And becauſe hee hath vouchſafed to accept mee for his ſeruant and friend, and hath honoured mee with ſuch an office, that it wold likewiſe pleaſe him to giue mee the ſpirite of <hi>Humilitie,</hi> who might draw and turne away my mind from pride, &amp; from all that doeth diſpleaſe him: to the end my ſeruice bee not to his diſhonour, but to his honour and glorie, giuing mee that, which he knoweth to bee moſt needefull vnto me, &amp; that which hee is willing I ſhould haue to his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, for to be more accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto him. And this I doe for no other cauſe, but that I might liue and die w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him, &amp; feare not to bee
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:22575:125"/>caſt (although I haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued it) out of his ſight and fauour. Then after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde I pray to him for my frendes and acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, as alſo for all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that it would pleaſe him in his mercie to giue them grace, that they all ſhoulde praiſe, honour, loue and thanke him, as is their duetie: endeuour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelfe for to doo and ſpeake all this with all pureneſſe and ſimplicitie of minde. What doe you quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> to come by ſuch purenes? To my vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt, anſwered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Loue of God,</hi> I haue a ſpeciall care to my minde, &amp; keep a ſtraight watch ouer al my cogitations, and doe moſt carefully looke to my ſoule.
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:22575:126"/>And beſides, I ſuruey narrowly all my ſenſes, ſetting alwaies before my eie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Sincerity,</hi> who turneth all things which ſhe ſeeth to the beſt. And when I will aſſure my ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the worlde, and haue no cauſe to feare any body: then I go and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine with my Lord, for it is all my comforte, ioy, pleaſure, and my Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taigne good, to bee in his company to ſpeake, and aſke his aduice and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell: and I am neuer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, quiet, ſatiſfied, or aſſured, but when I am with him. And therefore I haue determined to leaue &amp; forſake all things for to dwell and remaine with him, and neuer to go
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:22575:126"/>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, but when he doth commaunde it me. It is yet quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times needful to reade al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It is true, aunſwered the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is good, not for to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come craftie and ſubtill thereby, but onely for to learne to know God and his waies, &amp; to loue him as wee ſhoulde. And to this I neede not manye bookes, but will deepely fal in loue with my Lord, and ſet all my deſire and whole minde vppon him, with all my vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and wiſedome, for his loue doeth ſuffice me, and will inſtruct mee in all thinges, which are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitte for mee to know: and he will by the means
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:22575:127"/>of loue, diſcloſe and open vnto me, more ſecreates, then all the bookes of the world are able to do. And my ſoule gathereth more pureneſſe, feare, feruency, reuerence, repentaunce, ſtrength and force to reſiſt my fleſhe, when I am w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him, then whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I do read. Beſides, I know that he neuer wil aſke an account how much I haue reade &amp; ſtudied, but how I haue honoured and loued him, yet hereby I will not ſeem to condemne readinge, chiefly in thoſe who know not the wayes of God, nor the gouernemente of the ſpirite, nor cannot frame in good order their thoughtes, wordes and deedes, as they ſhould do,
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:22575:127"/>to thoſe I ſay, it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhoulde read a long time to becom pro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt &amp; ready in ſpirituall &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward exerciſes. For other wiſe it would bee a great madnes, preſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: nay, a contempt &amp; diſpiſing o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a clowniſh fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe who knoweth not the vſe, cuſtome, and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the court, would come perſonally to ſpeake with the king, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of all his Lords &amp; nobles, &amp; now being in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> midſt of his talke, ſhould caſt forth vnwiſe &amp; fooliſh words ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cording vnto his cuſtome, for this ſhoulde turne to his great ſhame &amp; confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, for the king woulde command him to be driue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away, ſo that it ſhould
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:22575:128"/>haue beene better for him neuer to haue preſumed to ſhew himſelf before his Maieſtie. And thus it is with ſpirituall matters. But thoſe that haue got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowledge of God, and of heauenly thinges, eyther by reading or hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring prayer, is much more profitable, &amp; a more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent an exerciſe then rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge, being now ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what acquainted with the manners, vſe and cuſtome vſed in the ſpirituall and heauenly Court.</p>
               <p>And when I am nowe before my Lorde, then I take heede that I turne not my head, eyes, &amp; body, hither and thether: becauſe it is a ſigne of contempt of his word, when one ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:22575:128"/>vnto him, and then turneth his face another way. Declare this vnto mee, quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what better, for I doe not wel vnderſtande it. When I, aunſwered the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> ſpeak vnto my Lord, and caſt my mind and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: then I turne him my backe, and not my face. Therefore I thinke and perſwade my ſelfe, that he alwaies ſeeth me, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer turneth his eyes from me, for to marke what I ſay, what ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy I haue, what reuerence I ſhewe vnto him, likewiſe in what repentance, loue &amp; vnitie, I doe exerciſe my ſelfe. Then afterwarde I humbly thanke him for all
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:22575:129"/>his benefits beſtowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, and generally vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all creatures, hauing them oftentimes in my minde, and rehearſing them vnto him: becauſe I knowe that hee cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide any vnthankefulnes, or that in any wiſe wee ſhould forget his goodnes declared vnto vs all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>The eight Chapter intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of the third degree of the Loue of God.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing I haue nowe ſpoken vnto thee of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt degree o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> loue which I beare vnto my Lorde, which is to be careful not
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:22575:129"/>to offend him, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of the ſeconde, which is to doe all that hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth mee, yet I am not contented with theſe two, for the great loue which I ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e him, but haue toyned vnto thoſe two firſt, the third degree which is, to do all that I am able to thinke or ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, for to pleaſe and to bee acceptable vnto him, wherby do you know qd <hi>Deſire,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you do y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is pleaſant in his ſight? By two things anſwered the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> The one is, to loue that which hee lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other, to hate y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which he hateth. As co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt, to loue that which he leueth, therby I loue my Lords only ſon,
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:22575:130"/>who is the faireſt, gentleſt and moſt worthieſt, that euer was or ſhal be, being like vnto his father in all thinges, and yet the moſt obedienteſt that was or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhall bee. This ſonne be loueth as much as hun ſelf, becauſe he is more like vnto him, then euer ſonne was vnto his father. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnitie and loue between the father and the ſonne is ſo exceeding great, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are both one, of one will, force, power, wiſedome &amp; maieſtie. And although they are diſtinguiſhed in perſons, are notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding but of one ſubſtance and eſſence. My Lorde did make with his owne hande for this his ſonne, a ſhepheardes garmente
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:22575:130"/>wherewithall being clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed, came out of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers chamber, yet neuer was from him, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies with him, and is dayly conuerſant with vs in this houſe, for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we could not ſee nor know him: and thus ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parelled, his father ſent him with a baſket at his armes through the whole world, &amp; likewiſe through this wilderneſſe to ſeeke out his ſheepe that were loſt and run aſtray. And as hee was walkinge through the deſart, his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuffered him to bee ſlaine by the wolues, and deuoured by dogges, and in no wiſe would come to aid or aſſiſt him, although hee was able enough to
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:22575:131"/>haue done it, but his will was, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the wolues ſhould teare him in peeces, and put him to the moſt cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt death that could be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented or imagined, and ſhoulde vſe him the worſe becauſe hee was a kinges ſonne. And this did our Lord for meer loue which hee bare vs, becauſe that all they which are of his houſhold might perceiue and ſee howe dearely hee loued vs, in that he hath not ſpared his owne ſon, but hath giuen him in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for vs, therefore are we bound to loue him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, becauſe he loued, vs ſo much before. when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Loue of God</hi> was telling this, <hi>Deſire</hi> wept bitterly, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his hart ſeemed to breake
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:22575:131"/>in peeces. The father lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſon ſo much, ſaide y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Loue of God,</hi> that although he ſuffred him to be put to death, yet throgh his om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotency did ſoone raiſe him vp again fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> more glozie and triumph the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euer before, carrying w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him thoſe ſheepe, for whom bee was come, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a ſpeciall care ouer thoſe whome hee had yet left in the deſarte and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures to waxe fat. And thus he returned into his fathers chamber, where he now ſitteth at his right hand, making dayly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion for vs, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing our infirmities for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnſpeakable loue which he beareth vnto ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kind: &amp; I belieue that if it were
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:22575:132"/>not for his ſake, the Lorde would haue caſt vs long agone out of this houſe, for our great wickedneſſe ſake, becauſe we ſerue him ſo negligently, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie zeale or affection, and ſo highly doe forget him, &amp; put him out of minde for euery trifle and ſmall oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion. The Father lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth his ſonne ſo dearely, that I belieue not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is any thing in this world wherwith we can do him better ſeruice, then in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of his ſonne. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I endeuour my ſelfe to loue &amp; pleaſe his ſonne. wherein, quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> do you loue and pleaſe him? when I, aunſwered the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> remember his holy life, his exceeding
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:22575:132"/>great trauaile, his death, &amp; his bleſſed doctrine, &amp; endeuor to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>form &amp; frame my actions and manners vnto his life, for when my Lord doeth ſee one reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling the life of his ſonne ſo much the more doth he loue him: and therefore it was his wil that he ſhold come to viſite vs, dwel w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs, and teach vs how we ſhoulde liue, for wee liued before euen as beaſts, and therfore the Lord did ſend him vnto vs, in ſteed of a mirror, and looking glaſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all men who were deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to knowe whether their wil, or actions were bad or good, ſhoulde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold his ſons life, for in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde there is no ſurer &amp; better, touchſtone then it.
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:22575:133"/>The ſeconde whome my Lord loueth, is my page, called <hi>Neighbourly loue</hi> For hee loueth this lad ſo tenderly, that all that we doe vnto him, whether it be good or euill, he doth take it as it were done vnto his own perſon. In what loue you this boye, quoth <hi>Deſire.</hi> Firſt ol al, I eſteeme him to bee bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then my ſelfe, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I doe ſupplie a great and high office, yet am obedient vnto him in all lawfull &amp; good things. I take heede in no wiſe to hinder or endamage him, but I ſhewe him all loue and frend ſhippe that I am able. I haue no ill ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pition of him, but rather doe alwayes defende and
<pb n="255" facs="tcp:22575:133"/>excuſe him. I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>narie him not i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> words nor dee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, but I ſuffer patiently his naturall weaknes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>rie him, I doe not back <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e him, nor will not ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r any man for to do it. I wiſh that he ſhould exceede me in loue which I beare to God, and that it woulde pleaſe almightie God to make him better then my ſelfe. I in no wiſe ennie his temporall or ſpirituall bleſſinges, or any thing that belongeth vnto him, but reioyce in his proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and welfare, his loſſe aduerſitye and ſorrowe doeth hartely grieue mee. Further, I thinke him to be an Angell of the Lord, and that I am vnworthy
<pb n="256" facs="tcp:22575:134"/>to bee his ſlaue &amp; ſeruant, and this do I becauſe my Lord loueth him ſo deore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. I loue alſo the affaires of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> common wealth, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge a ſpeciall care ouer them, becauſe they apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to the ſeruice of the Lorde, to his honour and to the mayntenance of his houſe. Therefore I doe mine indeuour that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be neglected, chiefly which concerneth anye godly exerciſe, as is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, faſting, chaſtning of the fleſh, and ſuch like, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſome do but little eſteeme of theſe thinges. Further I remember y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I know him better then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other creature, becauſe I haue receyued more at his handes then any. And
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:22575:134"/>ſeeing that other ſeruants ſerue their earthly maiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, with greate atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance and diligence, why ſhoulde I not ſerue my Lord, who hath choſen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e to bee his chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine aboue any domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſeruant? And although all the world ſhould faile, and there ſhould none bee remayning, yet I will neuer be vnfaithfull vnto him till death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>The ninth Chapter intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of thoſe things which the loue of God hath, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the concluſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He other of theſe two things wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vnto thee,
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:22575:135"/>and wherewith I ſeeke to pleaſe my Lord, is to hate y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> which he hateth. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſet before mee, that my Lorde hath two ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, the one, the world, the other my fleſh, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I haue determined w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my ſelfe to hate them mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally, &amp; neuer to contracte any league with them: &amp; becauſe I might the ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſter remaine in my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination, I uſe theſe meanes, neuer to recreate my ſelfe with them, to ſpeake or frequent their companies, vnieſſe my Lord doeth commaund it me, whoſe commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I eſreene more then my determination. And therefore I haue deſired y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lieuetenant of the houſe,
<pb n="259" facs="tcp:22575:135"/>that be ſend me not about ſuch buſines whereby I might recreatemy ſelfe, as in townes, citties, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, or among people, for I eſteeme this a great contempt and diſpiſing, but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I am co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded, then I obey. And althogh my Lorde for certaine af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires commandeth me to go into the world, yet his will is, that I in going ſhould not loyter, and in returning ſhold be found faithfull vnto him, and in no wiſe ſhold vſe any falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood practiſe treaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, but ſhoulde withdrawe my ſelfe as ſoone as it were poſſible, &amp; come again, for I know certainely, that how nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly wee looke to
<pb n="260" facs="tcp:22575:136"/>our ſelues, and as much good as we can do, yet we are like to get there no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but are alwaies in danger to looſe much. In this ſorte I hate like my ſins, iniquities, vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, carnal motions, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes deſires and vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall paſſions, and am ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie penſiue and ſorrowful that they dwel within me, knowing that they are contrary to my Lords wil &amp; doe altogether diſpleaſe him. Therefore I ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour my ſelfe alwayes to amend through loue. Like wiſe for the loue of him I eſchewe and flie from all thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are in his houſe, except it be in thinges of neceſſitie and loue, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing my ſelfe altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="261" facs="tcp:22575:136"/>from them. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doe you ſo, quoth <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire.</hi> Becauſe now a dayes there are no ſpiritual prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, loue and goodly zeale practiſed and exerciſed, and thoſe that boaſt of the knowledge of God, commonly decay in ſlothfulnes</p>
               <p>Therefore I will accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome my ſelfe to be alone, and addict my ſelf to prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that my ſoule may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceine and feele ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and ioy in the Lorde, and I learne to loue him as it becommeth me, for to that intent I haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken the worlde, and all the vanities thereof. But quoth <hi>Deſire</hi> others will account you fantaſticall &amp; partiall, and euery man
<pb n="262" facs="tcp:22575:137"/>will caſt his eyes vppon you, it is no matter an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> for I ſhoulde not ſerue to pleaſe man, and chiefly in things which are contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to God. And when I giue no offence to my brother, I care not what the worlde ſpeaketh, ſo I do my duety in that which is commanded mee, And therefore if thou wilt haue and poſſeſſe me, doe as I do.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="263" facs="tcp:22575:137"/>
               <head>The tenth Chapter intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, that the Loue of God brought De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to the houſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DEſire</hi> was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſed at thoſe things which the <hi>Loue of God</hi> had tolde him, and after long ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying, ſaid: When you do all theſe things, haue you then any need to ſtand in feare of any body? I truly aunſwered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Loue of God,</hi> for I muſt be very careful that I bee not puſt vp in vaine glorie for my good workes, or intangled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſelfe loue, for if I gaue anye place unto theſe,
<pb n="264" facs="tcp:22575:138"/>my Lord preſently would thruſt and turne me out of the doores. There<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore I haue alwayes at my ſide my mother <hi>Humilitie.</hi> I pray you quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> to leade mee into the houſe, follow me ſaid the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> for thou haſt beene nowe long enough with me, and I will bring thee to another of my fellowes who hath a greater office then I. How is he called quoth <hi>Deſire.</hi> His name anſwered the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> is <hi>To deſire God. Deſire</hi> went merrely accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Loue of God,</hi> to ſeeke out <hi>To deſire God,</hi> &amp; when he had found him: ſaid vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him: my Lord I wold it would pleaſe you to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine me as one of your
<pb n="265" facs="tcp:22575:138"/>ſeruantes. <hi>Deſires</hi> good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will did greatly pleaſe <hi>To deſire God,</hi> and ſaide vnto him, it is needefull (ſo y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wilt bee with me) that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> bee firſt well inſtructed by my fellows, for thou muſt knowe, that of the wine which floweth out of the hoggeſhead of the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> is made <hi>To deſire God.</hi> Therefore doe not deceiue thy ſelfe, but ſee y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou be firſt well prouided and repleniſhed with the <hi>Loue of God.</hi> My Lorde quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> I haue dwelt longe with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Loue of God,</hi> and he hath inſtructed me in all thinges which I muſt doe, and with Gods grace I wil endeuour my ſelfe to put all thinges in vre and practiſe, but I
<pb n="266" facs="tcp:22575:139"/>cannot warrant you whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I haue the <hi>Loue of God,</hi> or not, for hee onely knoweth who doeth loue him, and in theſe thinges the veſt is to humble him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. As for my ſelfe I can not aſſure what I haue, but onely this dog called <hi>good-wil,</hi> and yet I think not that hee is mine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was but ſent me. <hi>To deſire God</hi> did take a great delight and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in all theſe wordes, and chiefly becauſe <hi>Deſire</hi> did not perſwade himſelf that he had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Loue of God,</hi> I pray you Sir, quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> to tell me your na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and conditions. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as a man ſaide, <hi>The derſie of God</hi> commeth through the knowledge
<pb n="267" facs="tcp:22575:139"/>of himſelfe to a hate and deſpiſing of himſelfe, ſo likewiſe through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, hee attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to Deſire God. And whoſoeuer doeth poſſeſſe mee, hee hated all worldly thinges, for I do frame in him ſo noble and excellent a mind, that hee thinketh himſelfe to good, to deſire any thing els, then the chiefeſt and the ſoueraineſt good, which is God one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, beſides I make him very great &amp; high tanored w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God, &amp; although he is but of baſe kindred, yet I make him a mighty king, &amp; whoſoeuer doeth enioy me, his mind runneth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nothing but vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he ſpeketh nothing but of God, for where his trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="268" facs="tcp:22575:140"/>is, there is his, hart al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo. And that which a man hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiued in mind, the congue commonly ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, for the mouth doeth alwaies bewray the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde affections of the hart. To the hungrie I am meat, and reſtoritie, I am the chiefeſt in this pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, and ain Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine to loue and <hi>Charitie,</hi> I haue power to bringe thoſe in, whome I will that are my frendes. I am the preacher, who goeth through the houſe trying, vntill my Lorde doeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake, &amp; commeth forth of his chamber, for to ſpeake with thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do call vpon him. Whom think you did awake vs, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou didſt ſtand long before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gates,
<pb n="269" facs="tcp:22575:140"/>knocking with the two hammers hanging at the doore, called <hi>To ſigh and weepe,</hi> but onely the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual barking of thy dog. I am the ſureſt meſſinger, who commeth firſt at the gates, and goeth to the Lord, who followeth him alwaies, and is next vnto him. I haue in my power the fruite of a tree, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which wee that are here within haue to deliuer out, and to giue to euery man there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to eate, called <hi>See God.</hi> Is it a ſweete fruite, ſaid <hi>Deſire,</hi> for they gaue me an other to eat in the houſe of <hi>Humility,</hi> which was ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what bitter: and chiefly at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt fell ſomewhat harde &amp; vneaſie to bee ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. This fruite quoth hee
<pb n="270" facs="tcp:22575:141"/>
                  <hi>To deſire God,</hi> is maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſweete and pleaſant, but to ſome more ſweeter, and of pleaſanter taſt then to others, which happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth after the good appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite and ſtomack that they haue. And the ſounder y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their taſt is, and their teeth the better, thereafter they finde this fruite the ſweeter and more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant. For ſome there are, who haue rotten teeth, &amp; to thoſe this fruit is vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorie, for they are not able to chaw it. And ſome doe eat it without appetite or hunger, becauſe their ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mackes are already ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laden with other meates, and to thoſe likewiſe it is vnpleaſant, becauſe they cannot well digeſte it, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="271" facs="tcp:22575:141"/>it doeth them but ſinal hurt. And ſome there are, whoſe taſte is marde through a feuer, or an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall heate, and theſe knowe nothing of this fruit, but onely by heare ſay. I pray you qd <hi>Deſire,</hi> let me taſte of this fruit. I am glad anſwered <hi>To de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d,</hi> art thou willing to taſte of it, for it is not poſſible, that wee during this life ſhould ſatiſfie our ſelues, or ſil our bellies w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it, but only taſt how ſweet and pleaſant it is. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore quoth <hi>Deſire?</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore aunſwered <hi>To deſire God,</hi> for if man could here ſatiſfie his appetite with it, &amp; feede plentifully vnto his owne will of it: hee wold neuer be willing to
<pb n="272" facs="tcp:22575:142"/>leaue this priſon, and go to heauen, hauing here of this fruit ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t enough to maintaine him. But for the better vnderſtanding hereof, we die almoſt for hunger, and are famt and feeble w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> too long faſting, looking alwaies for the time till we ſhall come to the banquet of our ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lorde and Ring. And euen as a hart doth thirſt in the Sommer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſpringe of water: ſo likewiſe doe our ſoules hunger after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> day. This fruite is of ſuch force and vertue, that onely a ſmall bitte doth fil our ſtomacke ſo much, that it is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to containe more, how great a feeder ſoeuer a man bee. But when wee
<pb n="273" facs="tcp:22575:142"/>ſhall bee with the Lorde, then he will giue vs grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter &amp; ſtronger ſtomackes, that we may eat plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enough of theſe fruites, without any hurt or ſurfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: for if any would eate here in this li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, more then their ſtomackes were able to beare: it woulde more hinder then profite them. Therefore it is needefull, that we eat but a little and inoderatly of theſe fruits, till we come to that place, where we may fully ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie our ſelues with them, wherof we haue now but a taſte onely.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="274" facs="tcp:22575:143"/>
               <head>The eleuenth Chapter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treateth how to Deſire God, did prepare Deſire for to eate of the fruit.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
                  </hi> Pray you ſir quoth <hi>Deſire.</hi> let mee haue a taſte of theſe fruits ſo much or little as it pleaſeth you. Firſt aunſwered <hi>To deſire God,</hi> becauſe this fruit doth neuer remain but in a pure veſſell, it is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moſt neceſſary that thou doeſt make cleaue thy teeth, waſh thy eyes, mouth, face, and handes. But where ſhall I come to water here ſaide <hi>Deſire,</hi>
                  <pb n="275" facs="tcp:22575:143"/>I will bring thee to a fountaine of life, aunſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>To deſire God,</hi> which runneth and floweth both night and day, and is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Godly exerciſe,</hi> beſides I will call ſome Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelles of the houſe, that will bee willing to waſh and cleanſe thee: <hi>Deſire</hi> was glad in tarrying for theſe Damſelles, and ſaw preſently <hi>To deſire God,</hi> accompainied with theſe Ladies: and ſaide, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold frende theſe Ladies muſt waſh thee. The firſt is called <hi>Courteſie,</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde <hi>Vnitie,</hi> the third <hi>Pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> the fourth <hi>Mercy,</hi> the fift <hi>Amiableneſſe,</hi> the ſixte <hi>Fauour,</hi> the ſeuenth <hi>Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> the eight <hi>Zeale,</hi>
                  <pb n="276" facs="tcp:22575:144"/>the ninth <hi>Ioy,</hi> the tenth <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,</hi> the eleuenth <hi>Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> twelfth <hi>Prouidence</hi> or <hi>Forecaſt.</hi> And this laſt will giue thee an hearbe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> will prouoke thine appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, for to eat thy meat w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a better ſtomacke. For this fruite is onely mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to the hungrie, and not to any other. The thirteenth Damſell is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Long</hi> ſuffering, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth <hi>Conſtancie,</hi> the fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth <hi>Peace,</hi> the ſixteenth <hi>Neatnes,</hi> the ſeuenteenth <hi>Diligence,</hi> the eighteenth <hi>Prayer,</hi> the nineteenth <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,</hi> and the laſt am I to <hi>Deſire God.</hi> And I am al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies found in this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany And ſo long as thou art to bee founde among them, they will further
<pb n="277" facs="tcp:22575:144"/>thee greatly in the eating of this fruite. And when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer thou doſt eat them, they will goe alwaies with thee, and neuer forſake thee, vnleſſe thy ſelfe beares them away, and doeſt miſuſe them, for they themſelues are wondrous deſirous of this diet, and no ſooner they fee this fruite, but preſently they ſwarme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, ene<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as bees about the hony, and there is no ſurer token that one hath had a taſt of theſe fruites, but when they ſee theſe Damſels about the doore. <hi>Deſire</hi> was glad when hee was waſht, and had taſted of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruit. Brother quoth <hi>to deſire God,</hi> ſeeing thou haſt done this, thou muſt
<pb n="278" facs="tcp:22575:145"/>now ſing alſo, for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of God do alwaies ſing after their meales, praiſing and thanking the Lord. And h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at can not one in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that can not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Howe ſhall I ſing quoth <hi>Deſire,</hi> Let vs goe within the houſe, ſaid <hi>To deſsire God,</hi> where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll the Muſicians dwell. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rſt is called <hi>Bleſſing,</hi> the ſecond <hi>Honour,</hi> the thirde <hi>Prayſe,</hi> the fourth <hi>Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing.</hi> With theſe muſt thou ſing, for they are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good and ſkilfull Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians, and haue all good doyces. The firſt Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian called <hi>Bleſſing,</hi> ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Superins or troble and prayſeth God for his great liberalitie. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde who ſupplieth the
<pb n="279" facs="tcp:22575:145"/>Contratenor called <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> praiſeth the Lord for his vnſpeakeable and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bom. And the third who is c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Praiſe,</hi> ſingeth the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, and praiſeth him in his endles goodnes, boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, excellency, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally in all that God is in himſelfe. The ſourth is <hi>Thankeſgiuing,</hi> and ſerueth the Baſe, who thanketh the Lorde for all that hee hath created, and for all his benefites moſt liberal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly powred &amp; beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vppon all his creatures.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="280" facs="tcp:22575:146"/>
               <head>The twentie two Chapter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treateth howe Deſire did learne to ſing.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He muſicke and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner thereof did pleaſe <hi>Deſire</hi> great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly. Behold quoth <hi>to deſire God,</hi> wilt thou go hence, and return againe from whence thou art come, where ſhould I trauaile anſwered <hi>Deſire,</hi> for to be better then I am here where I am come w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo much pain and labour? Now that I am welcome to a place where I may line in quiet, and be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, I am not minded to change, for they ſay in
<pb n="281" facs="tcp:22575:146"/>a common prouerbe. De y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is in bliſſe, let him remain where hee is. And I tell you ſir, I wil not go he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, vnles you doe thruſt mee out of the dores. It is not our cuſtome, qd <hi>To deſire God,</hi> to turn any body out of the doores, vnleſſe they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues doe deſire it, but rather doe intreat them to ſtay. But becauſe they may know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſtand not in need of any body, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſometimes doe aske them, if they are deſirous for to go or not. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou art willing to tarrie here with vs, thou muſt not bee idle. what muſt I doe qd <hi>Deſire.</hi> All y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhall commande thee aunſwered <hi>To deſire God.</hi> And when I ſhall not bee
<pb n="282" facs="tcp:22575:147"/>commaunded at all, ſaide <hi>Deſire,</hi> what ſhall I doe then? Sing anſwered <hi>To deſire God,</hi> praiſe, thanke &amp; magnifie the Lord. And whenſoeuer y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art about thy buſines, &amp; doſt that is commanded vnto then, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou maieſt yet ſing to thy ſelfe, for to keepe thy thoughtes from idlenes. Further wilt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> pleaſe our Lord, and become his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar frende, ſee y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou goeſt to ſpeak oftentimes alone w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him, and if y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> wilt profite greatly, bee daylie conuerſant w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him. Then ſhalt thou heare his aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, who will diſcloſe vnto thee many ſecretes, whereby y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt grow fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar with him, &amp; becom one of his minions. May
<pb n="283" facs="tcp:22575:147"/>euery man who will, ſaid <hi>Deſire,</hi> come in his cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and ſpeake with him? I quoth <hi>To deſire God,</hi> as far as he hath <hi>Humilitie</hi> in his company, I tel thee y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is his greateſt ioy y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wee ſhould come to him, and awake him, for hee is of this nature y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide to be alone, and how baſe &amp; ſimple ſoeuer a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is, yet he reioyceth great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his company, and will haue him to remaine with him continually. For his nobilitie and worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is ſo great, that hee doth not regarde the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall perſon, for there is no exceptions of perſons with him, if his ſpirite bee humble: for one man hath coſt him ſo deare as an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="284" facs="tcp:22575:148"/>and hath created the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all of one ſubſtance, the earth. I which more is, the baſer &amp; viler the perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is, if he doth but debaſe &amp; humble himſelf, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fauour and courteſy he ſheweth vnto him, and wil do him the more good. And I tell thee plaine, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the moſt part of theſe, that are dwelling here, are but of ſimple pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genie. For God hath cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen thoſe for his ſeruice, who were the abiectes of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> worlde, to the ende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no body who dwelleth here ſhould think him to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued and intertained for his deſarts &amp; worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but only through the goodneſſe and meere mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God. Therefore if y<hi rend="sup">u</hi>
                  <pb n="285" facs="tcp:22575:148"/>art willing for to dwell here, and deſirous not to looſe, but to profite &amp; fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thy ſelfe, and procure that thy ſong bee accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto God, remember theſe four parts. The firſt is <hi>Good-will,</hi> the ſeconde <hi>Humilitie,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> third <hi>Patience,</hi> the fourth <hi>Loue</hi> or <hi>Charity.</hi> And whenſoeuer thou ſingeſt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe four parts, thou ſhalt neuer faile in thy ſongs. And although ſometimes y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> flippeſt a note or two, or els doeſt not ſing faſt enough, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently thou ſhalt come to the right tune againe by hearing onely. With <hi>good will</hi> thou ſhalt ſing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perius or Treble, for all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> reſt doth frame it ſelfe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it, and with the ſecond
<pb n="286" facs="tcp:22575:149"/>and third, namely w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility</hi> &amp; <hi>Patience,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt ſing the Contratenor, for <hi>Humilities</hi> &amp; <hi>Patiences</hi> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges are contrarie to a mans wil and wilfulnes. And w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the fourth, namely <hi>Loue,</hi> thou ſhalt ſing all manner of muſicke what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, &amp; that w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy ſoule. &amp; the ſweetneſſe of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> holy Ghoſt. But aboue all thinges doe not forget to eat the fruit, which thou haſt eaten in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pallace of <hi>Humilitie,</hi> namely to <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt in thy ſelfe,</hi> and the greater thy loue and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire is towards God, and the greater friend thou art of the Lord, giue him the more of this fruite, for he loueth them wel, &amp; gladly eateth of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="287" facs="tcp:22575:149"/>
               <head>The thirteenth chapter, how to deſire God, did bring Deſire into the chamber of the Lord, &amp; beſides in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treateth of an inſtruction to Praier.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
                  </hi> woulde praye you for to get one ſauoure more at your hands, which is, ſeeing you haue enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained mee, &amp; granted y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſhall dwell here, that it may pleaſe you likewiſe to bring me to my Lord, for to know him, &amp; to do vnto him homage &amp; reuerence. I am contented, qd <hi>To De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire God,</hi> go w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me. <hi>Deſire</hi> went trembling y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he now ſhould ſpeak w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo mightie a king &amp; monarch in his
<pb n="288" facs="tcp:22575:150"/>chamber, and ſtand before his diuine maieſty, and was taken w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch feare &amp; trembling, that he neither durſt nor coulde come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Lorde, in as much y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hee was minded to turne backe againe. But when he remembred againe the nobilitie and vnſpeakable courteſie and goodnes of this king, &amp; how louing &amp; affable<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hee was to euery man, he comforted himſelf vppon his gratiouſneſſe, there vpon putting onely all his truſt &amp; confidence. Tarrie for mee here at the doore, ſaide <hi>to deſire God,</hi> for I will go ſee what my Lorde doth, and tell him how y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art here to ſpeak w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him, <hi>Deſire</hi> was yet fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſtudying what hee
<pb n="289" facs="tcp:22575:150"/>ſhould ſay vnto the Lord, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhold come before him. Com hither qd <hi>to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire God,</hi> I haue tolde my Lorde how y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art here. Go in therfore, and I wil ſtay here for thee. <hi>Deſire</hi> began w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great reuerence to goe through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chamber of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, &amp; as ſoone as he did ſee the Lorde, fell downe flat vpon his face weeping bitterly, &amp; durſt not once lift vp his eyes, for he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had beene a mortall enemye of his Lord, &amp; had done him of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes great iniury and wrong, in as much that he was not able to vtter one word, but onely did ſigh &amp; weepe, thinking alwaies y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> now he was in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of this endleſſe good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<pb n="290" facs="tcp:22575:151"/>whome hee had ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes, &amp; ſo grieuouſly offended. What meaneth this, qd our Lord, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doeſt thou come he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? doeſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> not ſpeak? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, &amp; let me know thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire. What can or ſhall I ſpeake before thy incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible Maieſtie? an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered <hi>Deſire.</hi> O my Lord I am not worthy to open my vile &amp; vnclean mouth in thy ſight, but ſuffer me now to bewaile by ſilence, ſighes, &amp; teares, my fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt wickednes &amp; iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Wherefore art y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> come hither quoth our Lord? I I am not come hither my Lord, anſwered <hi>Deſire,</hi> for I do not thinke, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue deſerued to dwell here in thy houſe, and yet leſſe to
<pb n="291" facs="tcp:22575:151"/>come in thy maieſties cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, &amp; preſence. Who hath bronght thee hether then ſaid our Lord: Thy grace hath drawne mee hether, hath cauſed me to be calde, &amp; commanded to let mee come in, &amp; to haue acceſſe vnto thee. I cannot tell my Soueraigne, what cauſe hath moued thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie here vnto, or where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thy grace hath neede of me, for it would ſuffice me &amp; bee too much, that ſuch a one as I am, might be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt of the ſeruants of thy houſe, &amp; yet deſerue not ſo much, and am altogether vnworthy of it. But ſeeing thy goodneſſe hath nowe called me, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> inpleaſeth thee, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſhold dwell heere &amp; ſpeake vnto thee, open
<pb n="292" facs="tcp:22575:152"/>y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> my lips, and teach mee what I haue to ſay in thy preſence, powre in me y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit of feare &amp; reuerence, to the end thy Maieſty be not offended, or in diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor ſerued by me, &amp; diſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of ſuch a wicked and vile ſinner as I am. Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I would be ready to ſuffer a thouſande deathes then to offend and deſpiſe thy highnes. For hereby I ſhoulde diſhonour and iniury the Angels, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angelles, &amp; all Celeſtiall powers, who intirely loue thy goodnes: &amp; ſerue the w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch zeale, glorie, &amp; reuerence. Declare vnto me O Lord, what I ſhall ſpeake &amp; direct mee in all my doings, for I commit my ſelfe wholly into thy
<pb n="293" facs="tcp:22575:152"/>hands, yeelding my ſoule &amp; body wholly vnto thy maieſty. Giue me O Lord y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpirite of Humilitie, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end I may ſerue thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation and children y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better, and that my ſeruice may bee pleaſant &amp; accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in thy ſight for thy names ſake, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty may bee honoured &amp; praiſed in me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>The fourteenth Chapter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treateth of the inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which our Lorde did giue vnto Deſire, for to rule and gouerne him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Riſe, quoth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord to <hi>Deſire</hi> and feare no more: and if thou hereafter
<pb n="294" facs="tcp:22575:153"/>wilt become a new man, &amp; ſuch a one as y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> oughteſt to bee, then I will reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber no more the iniury which y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt done me, and put out of my memorie all thy miſdeedes &amp; offences, wherewithall y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued me ſo oftentimes. But becauſe y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> inaieſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend and becom better, I wil teach thee foure words which will not profit thee a little, if thou doeſt reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and printeſt them in thy hart. Take theſe two, <hi>I,</hi> and <hi>thou,</hi> which are the two firſt: and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other two <hi>Slaue</hi> and <hi>King.</hi> And if y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> canſt rightly put theſe words in practiſe, they will bringe thee to great vertue &amp; perfection, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende thee againſt all thy
<pb n="295" facs="tcp:22575:153"/>naturall and vnbrideled affections, &amp; cauſe thee to remaine and liue w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery man in peace &amp; vnitie. I pray thee, my onely Lord, and Soueraigne, qd <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire,</hi> that it may pleaſe thee to ſhew vnto me, howe I might beſt exerciſe my ſelf with theſe foure wordes? Thou mayeſt refer all thy exerciſe to theſe words, for they contain in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a great and deepe knowledge, whereof one might write great volumes, and whereby without bookes one might likewiſe attain to great perfection, Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whenſoeuer y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meſt to ſpeak with me, or goeſt about any thing which is commanded thee, &amp; art al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together faint, cold, &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing
<pb n="296" facs="tcp:22575:154"/>then perſwade thy ſelf, that I do ſpeak to thee theſe words, <hi>I</hi> &amp; <hi>Thou</hi> &amp; no more: &amp; thus forget al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, &amp; think y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is no body in the worlde, but <hi>I</hi> and <hi>Thou.</hi> The other two wordes, <hi>Slaue</hi> &amp; <hi>King,</hi> ſhal ſerue thee, for to deale and frequent w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them: firſt of all, in imagining that y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> art Slaue vnto them all, and by theſe meanes thou ſhalt become humble and obedient. Secondly, that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art thine owne King, &amp; that I make all Kinges rich, &amp; beſtow vpon them pleaſure &amp; goods aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly. Let this inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at this time ſuffice thee, and thus depart in peace.</p>
               <p>Wherefore wilt thou O Lorde, that I ſhould goe
<pb n="297" facs="tcp:22575:154"/>away, ſaid <hi>Deſire,</hi> becauſe anſwered the Lord, thou ſhouldeſt not thinke that thou haſt deſerued it, and art worthy to remain al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies with me but ouely as long as I think good, or whenſoeuer I call or ſende for thee, to the end thou becom not preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous or vaine-glorious. Therefore whenſoeuer I will haue thee, I wil ſend for thee, yet before y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> goeft hence, leaue thy hart with me, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end in what place ſoeuer y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> commeſt, that the chiefeſt &amp; the beſt may ſtill remam w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me: I am here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto willing my Lord qd <hi>Deſire,</hi> I giue thee trancke and freely my whole hart. I am content anſwered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> now it remaine w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb n="298" facs="tcp:22575:155"/>me, but thinke not that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> canſt doe it ſo oftentimes as thou wilt thy ſelfe, and beſides I will neuer keep i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me without the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite and furtherance to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie. But yet of one thing, which thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt not, I will admoniſh thee, which is, the more croſſes, aduerſities and miſeries I lay vppon my ſeruantes, the wore ioy, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte &amp; bleſſednes I am minded and endeuour to beſtow vpon them. But wilt thou leaue thy dogge <hi>Good will</hi> here to mee, for will may he remain here if y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> commende him euery day vnto me, &amp; do not thy ſelfe take him away from me. Wherefore qd <hi>Deſire,</hi> is it neceſſarie to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mende
<pb n="299" facs="tcp:22575:155"/>him euery day vnto thee, once would it not ſuffice? No, anſwered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, not becauſe I ſhould forget it, but becauſe thou ſhouldſt not come to forget mee, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou mighteſt alwaies haue occaſion to haue mee in remembrance, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end I may do thee good, and com to ſuccor thee in time of thy trouble &amp; neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. For what doth it help or profite me, whether y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt mee in minde or not? I thanke thee my Lorde, qd <hi>Deſire,</hi> that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> doeſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint me before with thy wil and pleaſure, wherby onely thou worlieſt and bringeſt to paſſe in vs all things, as if thou ſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſeeme to ſtand in need of vs, where it is onely
<pb n="300" facs="tcp:22575:156"/>but to our profite and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>The fifteenth Chapter howe Deſire did exerciſe him in theſe foure wordes, and what profite hee rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped thereby.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eſire</hi> depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of the Lordes cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge: his hart behind him, and did finde <hi>to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire God</hi> watching at the doore. What haſt thou done ſo long within, qd <hi>to Deſire God.</hi> Doeſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> think that many wordes pleaſe the Lorde? Sometimes y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt doe more with one word with him, then with
<pb n="301" facs="tcp:22575:156"/>a hundreth. Ah Syr, aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered <hi>Deſire,</hi> I thinke that I haue not beene long with him. Go with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in anſwered <hi>to deſire God,</hi> ſeeing thou are nowe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained here. I will go into my chamber, ſaide <hi>Deſire.</hi> Go in the name of the Lord, quoth he. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire</hi> dayly remembred the foure wordes, which the Lorde had giuen him, oftentimes repeating <hi>I,</hi> and <hi>Thou, Slaue, King,</hi> and ſometimes did part, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founde, and mingle them together, but they fell al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies right, for hee tooke the one and ſaide <hi>I,</hi> and then the other <hi>Slaue.</hi> Yet I ſpeake right, quoth he, for I am for the loue of my Lorde a ſlaue. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="302" facs="tcp:22575:157"/>hee tooke the other and ſaide, <hi>I King.</hi> I do not miſſe yet, for I am a king, ſaid hee, being Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uante, for to ſerue him, is to commande, to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne, and to be a mighty Prince.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:22575:157"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
